<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A posie of spirituall flowers taken out of the garden of the holy scriptures, consisting of these sixe sorts: hearts ease, true delight, the worlds wonders, the souls solace, times complaint, the doom of sinners. Gathered for the encouragement of beginners, direction of proceeders, meditation of good hearers, consolation of true beleeuers, expectation of Sions mourners, confusion of irrepentant sinners. By George Webbe, minister of the word.</title>
            <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 226 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 107 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837926</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837926</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2273</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14860)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2273)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1045:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A posie of spirituall flowers taken out of the garden of the holy scriptures, consisting of these sixe sorts: hearts ease, true delight, the worlds wonders, the souls solace, times complaint, the doom of sinners. Gathered for the encouragement of beginners, direction of proceeders, meditation of good hearers, consolation of true beleeuers, expectation of Sions mourners, confusion of irrepentant sinners. By George Webbe, minister of the word.</title>
                  <author>Webbe, George, 1581-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 202 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted [by F. Kingston] for William Leake,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Six sermons, each with caption title: 1. A taste of happinesse. 2. True delight, or, the worlds farewell, and Christs welcome. 3. The worlds wonders. 4. The anchor of the soule. 5. The mourners lamentation. 6. The sinners doome.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:1"/>
                  <p>A POSIE OF SPIRITVALL FLOWERS, TAKEN OVT OF THE Garden of the holy Scriptures, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of theſe ſixe ſorts:
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Hearts eaſe,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>True delight,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Worlds won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Soules ſolace,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Times complaint,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The doom of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Gathered for the
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Encouragement of beginners,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Direction of proceeders,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Meditation of good hearers,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Conſolation of true beleeuers,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Expectation of Sions mourners,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Confuſion of irrepentant ſinners.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> By <hi>George Webbe,</hi> Miniſter of the Word.</p>
                  <p>AT LONDON, Imprinted for <hi>William Leake.</hi> 1610.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:2"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <p>Hearts eaſe.</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>A TASTE OF Happineſſe: Or BRIEF DESCRIPTION of that ſweetnes which Gods <hi>children doe finde in his ſeruice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Henry Bayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Knight, and his worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Ladie the Ladie <hi>Lucie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhipful, </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I ſhuld thinke my ſelfe excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding happie, if whiles the skilfull <hi>Bezaleels</hi> and <hi>Aho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liabs</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 36.1.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:2273:3"/>of our age doe adorne and beautifie the Sanctuarie of the Lord with their curious, rich, and worthie workes, I might but bring one ſticke or ſtone to the building of the ſame. But how great ſoeuer my deſire is, I am too well priuie to my ſelfe, <hi>quàm ſit mihi curta ſupellex,</hi> how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient all my ſufficiencie is. Whiles others lanch foorth into the deepe, it is fitteſt for me to ſit and mend my nettes at home:
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.21. Luke 21.1.</note> whiles the rich men caſt their gifts (as well they may) into the treaſurie, I haue but two mites (yea thoſe but ſmall ones alſo) to caſt in: One I haue alreadie caſt into the treaſurie, and it hath found acceptance; the other I am now to caſt in, (it is all that I haue) God grant it may obtaine the like fauourable countenance.
<pb facs="tcp:2273:3"/>A ſmaller mite there could not be, for I cannot call it a Work, nor a Treatiſe, nor ſo much as words, for they are but Thoughts, euen thoſe my meditating thoughts, which (according to <hi>Dauids</hi> counſell) at leiſure times,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> I haue communed with mine own heart in ſilence. That I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated them abroad and made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> publike, it was neither for any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie I deemed in them, nor for any vaine glorie I hunt after by the publiſhing of them. If any man otherwiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue of me and it, this is mine apologie,
<note place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I ſtand or fall to mine owne maſter.</hi> I was induced to the publiſhing of them, partly becauſe I haue perceiued by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce how much people are now delighted with this kinde of writings, and how great good hath been receiued
<pb facs="tcp:2273:4"/>from them, and partly that I might leaue ſome publike testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my thankfull minde to ſuch as in ample manner had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame at my hands. Wherein giue mee leaue (right Worſhipfull) in the firſt place to ſalute you both, by preſenting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the firſt of theſe my ſelected flowers: your kind acceptance of my other ſimple treatiſe dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to another, maketh mee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of your fauour vnto this which is dedicated to your ſelues. I preſent you here with a taſte of Happineſſe, an Enchiridion to make you more and more in loue with godlines,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.5.</note> that you may taſte how ſweete the Lord is, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taſted of that ſweetnes, may repoſe therein your chiefeſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Had I the tongue of men and Angels, I could not ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:2273:4"/>one halfe of that which they who taſte hereof enioy. Take a taſte then of this little taſte which here I haue prouided for you: expect not in it conceited cookerie, I ſeek to profit rather then to pleaſe; if you come with an appetite vnto it, though it want the ſauourie ſauce of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet will it relliſh well enough vnto you. The Lord God euermore prepare your hearts to receiue it, and grant a good dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to you in it.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Worſhips euer to commaund in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>G. W.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:5"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2273:5"/>
                  <head>A TASTE OF Happineſſe.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSAL. 34.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Taste and ſee how good the Lord is: Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> though otherwiſe an Iſraelite indeed, <hi>A man in whom there was no guile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 1.47.</note> yet herein had ſauored of a ſpice of incredulitie,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">45.</note>in that when <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> had brought him newes of our ſweet Sauiour,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">46.</note>whom long they had expected, and now found at Nazareth, it could not ſinke into his minde vpon the ſudden, that ſo faire a iewell ſhould bee found in ſo foule a place; <hi>Philip,</hi> to take away that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2273:6"/>ſcruple, willeth him to make his eyes the witneſſes of that which had bin related to his eares, that both his eyes and eares giuing ioynt teſtimonie hereof vnto his heart, he might not bee incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, but beleeue: <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſee.</hi> O that our ſcarſe half <hi>Nathaniels,</hi> who come far ſhort of him, and content themſelues only with a ciuill cariage of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, not ſeaſoned with reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, thinking that ſuperfluous, and obiecting; Can there any good thing come of godlineſſe? O that they would follow <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> counſell; would they would <hi>come and ſee.</hi> O that our earth-turmoiling <hi>Nabals,</hi> who no whit ſauour of <hi>Nathaniels</hi> ſpirit,
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.10.</note> but doting vpon theſe vnprofitable profits of the world, bluſh not to pollute the ayre with ſuch blaſphemous ſpeeches:
<note place="margin">Iob. 21.15.</note> 
                     <hi>VVho is the Almightie that we ſhould ſerue him? and what profit ſhould wee
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2273:6"/>haue if wee ſhould pray vnto him?</hi> which count it but a vaine thing to ſerue God, and demand of vs,
<note place="margin">Malach. 3 14.</note> 
                     <hi>What profit wee haue by keeping his commandements? and what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it is that wee walke humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord?</hi> O that they would take a little of <hi>Nathaniels</hi> paines to <hi>come and ſee:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 34 8.</note> or hearken vnto <hi>Dauids</hi> counſell; <hi>Oh that they would taſte and ſee how gratious and ſweete the Lord is;</hi> what a good maſter hee is whom the godly doe ſerue, what a good Prince he is whom the righteous doe obey, what a ſure carde he is on whom the faithfull truſt, how ſweete hee is to them that loue him, what a rewarder hee is to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare him, what a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter he is to them that depend vpon him. The vnexperienced ruſticke that neuer taſted Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Sugar, perceiueth no more ſweetneſſe in it, then there is in Allum; and <hi>Aeſops</hi> cock think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2273:7"/>better farre his graine of bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in the dunghill, then he doth eſtimate the richeſt pearle; and <hi>Baalams</hi> Aſſe that neuer taſted the ſweete fruite of Bees, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth there is much more ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in his thiſtle: and wretched ſoules, whoſe ſoules are out of taſte, and neuer made triall of the ſweetnes of the Lord, doe thinke, that <hi>plus Aloes quam mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis habet,</hi> that it hath much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes, and but little ſweetnes: Then, ſillie they, thinke nothing in heauen worth the hauing: the reaſon is, By groueling ſo much here on earth, they are ſo farre off, that all there is out of their kenning. The diet of a Chriſtian conuerſation, thinketh the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie and common Chriſtian, is but ordinarie and common fare; why ſhould we affect it? It is too ſtraite, ſaith the Libertine, wee cannot well endure it: It is too bitter, ſaith the wanton, wee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2273:7"/>cannot well digeſt it: It is too ſowre, ſaith the Epicure, and hath no pleaſure in it.</p>
                  <p>Alas poore ſoules, how are they all deceiued? and therefore decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe they neuer taſted it. For did they make a taſte hereof, they would then quickly proue it not a bondage, but a freedome; not bitter, but pleaſant; not ſowre but ſweete,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 19.10.</note> yea <hi>ſweeter then the honie and the honie combe:</hi> Did they once but take a perfect view hereof, with the wiſeſt <hi>Salomon,</hi> they would ſubſcribe and ſay, that neither <hi>the gold of Ophir,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prouerb. 8.12.</note> nor the mines of India, nor <hi>al the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures</hi> in the world were in any ſort to bee compared to it. Yea they would ſay with him that heere commendeth this taſte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 84.4, 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed are they which dwell in Gods houſe, for they will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer praiſe him: Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſtrength is the Lord; One day in Gods houſe is better then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2273:8"/>elſewhere:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">10.</note>It is better to be a doore-keeper in the houſe of our God, then to dwell in the tabernacles of wickedneſſe:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">11.</note>for the Lord God is the Sunne and ſhield vnto them, he will giue grace and glorie, and no good thing will hee withhold from them</hi> that haue taſted of him. His mercies to them are endleſſe, his fauors numberleſſe, his comforts infinite; he is glaſſe to their eies, muſicke to their eares, Honie to their mouth, Balme to their ſmel, contentation to their will, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation to their happineſſe.</p>
                  <p>When a man hath once taken a full taſte of him,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>No comfort in the world to the comfort of Gods children.</hi> Philip. 3.7. Eccleſ 1.1. Eccleſ 2.2. Philip. 3.8.</note> all worldlie dainties will ſeeme but vanities, all worldly gaines will ſeeme but loſſes, all worldly pleaſures will ſeeme but toyes, all worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights will ſeeme but madnes, all worldly treaſures will ſeeme but dungie traſh.
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 18.27.</note> The very taſte of this is like vnto <hi>Ionathans</hi> taſting of the honie combe, whereof
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2273:8"/>when he had put but a drop into his mouth, his dimme eyes were clarified to a quicker ſight: The taſte hereof is like vnto the Poets riuer <hi>Lethe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Virgil. Aeneid. lib.</hi> 6.</note> whereof whoſoeuer had a taſte, did ſoone forget all other delights and pleaſures. The taſte hereof made <hi>Peter</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that <hi>Bonum eſt eſſe hîc:
<note place="margin">Matth. 17.4.</note> It is good abiding here.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.3.</note> It made <hi>Paul</hi> in an ecſtaſie to forget whether he were in the bodie, or no: The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry taſte heereof is enough to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh the ſoule, and to cauſe it to ſay with <hi>Iacob, I haue enough,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 45 26.</note> I haue taſted of this, all other plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſeeme ſowre, to relliſh bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to be out of taſte.</p>
                  <p>O that I had now but <hi>Ananias</hi> his gift,
<note place="margin">Act. 9.17.</note> that to giue a glimſe of the eye-dazeling luſtre of this ſo glorious light, I could but touch the moleblind <hi>Sauls,</hi> the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme ſcoffers of this our age, and make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcales fall from their eyes; how cleerely ſhould they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2273:9"/>ſee,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>D. Eedes Sermon of heauenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſation.</hi> Philip. 3.20. 2. Cor. 1.12. Galat. 6.15. 1. Tim. 6.6. 1. Cor. 1.9. Reuel. 7. Pſalm. 34.8.</note> and ſeeing taſte, and taſting teſtifie, that there is no eſtate like to a Chriſtian conuerſation, no ioy to the ſolace of a religious heart, no peace to the peace of conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, no glorie to the croſſe of Chriſt, no riches to godlineſſe, no wiſedome to that of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, no pleaſures to the ſoule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, no ſweetnes to the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the Lord.</p>
                  <p>My ſoule,
<note place="margin">Greater ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the Lord, then at the first before the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it can be imagined.</note> thou muſt needes confeſſe, hadſt thou been put to thy choice before thou didſt feele a taſte heereof, thou couldeſt not haue asked or deſired the tenth part thereof; the Lord hath giuen more then I could aske or thinke, more then, had I all the tongues of men and Angels, I were able to expreſſe, yea more then any heart, but that which feeleth it, can beleeue. So that thou (my ſoule:) and what doe I ſpeake of mine? euery beleeuing ſoule can ſay no leſſe: as Shebaes Queene
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2273:9"/>ſaid of <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſedome,
<note place="margin">1. King. 6.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> ſo maiſt thou ſay of this ſweet taſte of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>It was a true word which I heard related to me</hi> of the moſt ſweet dainties of Gods children, when I was in mine owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, fedde with draffe, with fancies, and dreames and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleaſures; <hi>howbeit I beleeued not this report, till I came and ſaw it</hi> with mine eyes, and had a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and a taſte thereof: <hi>but loe now I ſee, the one halfe was not told me:</hi> for the ſweetnes I feele in the taſte hereof, doth farre ſurpaſſe al that euer mine eares did heare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of it, or mine heart could poſſibly imagine to be in it.</p>
                  <p>And whereas in other delicates ſatietie may breed lothſomneſſe,
<note place="margin">The longer it is enioied, the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is proued.</note> and the continuall vſe of one ſort of meate may glut the ſtomacke, in this taſte of the ſweetnes of the Lord, the longer I enioy it, the better I know it; the ſweeter I feele it, the more delight I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2273:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2273:10"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2273:11"/>in it, and receiue from it. The longer I taſte it, the more I am enamoured on it, &amp; ſtill more and more comfortable I proue it, like to <hi>Ezechiels</hi> riuer which hee ſaw iſſuing from vnder the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold of the temple,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 47.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> which at the firſt aroſe but to the ancles, then to the knees, afterwards to the loines, and at the laſt became a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which did ouerflow:
<note place="margin">Here in this life we can haue but a taſte.</note> And yet (my ſoule) here in this life whiles thou art ſoiourning in this vale of teares, thou canſt haue but a taſte;
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.9.12 <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> here thou canſt only know in part, and feele in part, and taſte in part, and ſee it but darkly as through a glaſſe: The full fruition thou ſhalt enioy when thou ſhalt come to ſing <hi>Haleluiahs</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with the quire of heauen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the King of heauen,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.4.</note> at whoſe <hi>right hand are fulnes of ioy for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> O ſweete Lord, if the taſte of thee bee ſo excellent, how ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perexcellent ſhall that ſweetnes
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2273:11"/>be,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.5. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>when I ſhall be ſatisfied with the fatnes of thine houſe, and drink out of the riuers of thy pleaſures?</hi> If the glimmering light of our happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe bee ſo glorious, how full of glorie ſhall the full proſpect be? If there bee ſo great ſolaces for thy children in theſe daies of teares, what ſhal there be in their day of mariage? If our iaile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuch ioyes, what ſhall our countrie and kingdome doe?</p>
                  <p>O my Lord and God thou art a good God,
<note place="margin">The infinite ſweetnes of the Lord.</note> 
                     <hi>How great is thy goodneſſe which thou haſt laid vp for them that feare thee, and done to them that put their truſt in thee,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.9.</note> euen before the ſonnes of men.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.5.</note> O Lord my God thy comforts are ſo many that none can count them, I would declare and ſpeake of them, but they are more then I am able to expreſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An vnwiſe man knoweth it not,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> think it otherwiſe.</hi> Pſal. 92.6.</note> and a foole doth not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this:</hi> An vnregenerate man
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2273:12"/>cannot feele it, and a child of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial,</hi> though he had eyes as cleere as Cryſtal, cannot behold it: Such as make ſinne their ſolace, and reioyce onely in the pleaſures of iniquitie, haue thy beloued ones, Lord,
<note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.4.</note> in deriſion, and count their life madneſſe, their conuerſation dumpiſh, their profeſſion grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous:
<note place="margin">Cantic. 5.9.</note> They ſay vnto vs, <hi>What is your welbeloued more then another welbeloued?
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> what is your welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued more then another Louer?</hi> Will they needes know it;
<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> why, <hi>Our welbeloued is white and ruddie, the chiefeſt of tenne thouſand,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 12. Verſ. 13.</note> his head is as fine gold, his locks curled and black as a rauen, his eyes are like doues vpon the riuers of waters,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> his cheekes are as a bed of ſpices, and as ſweete flowers, his lippes like lilies dropping downe pure myrrhe,
<note place="margin">Ver. 15.</note> his hands as rings of gold ſet with the Chryſolite,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> his hollie like white Iuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie couered with Saphires, his legges as marble ſet vpon ſockets of fine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2273:12"/>gold, his countenance as Lebanon, excellent as the Cedars; his mouth is as ſweete things, and he is totus delectabilis, whollie, whollie dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea thou our God art delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble all together,
<note place="margin">Nothing in God but full of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> ſweete art thou in thy word, ſweete in thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ſweet in thine inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, ſweete in thy mercies, ſweete in thy iudgements. <hi>How perfect is the law of the Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerring the ſoule!
<note place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note> The ſtatutes of uerting the ſoule! The ſtatutes of the Lord are right and reioyce the heart:
<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> The commandement of the Lord is pure, and giueth light vnto the eyes:
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> The feare of the Lord is cleane, and endureth for euer: The iudgements of the Lord are truth and righteous altogether, and more to be deſired the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gold, yea the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much fine gold, ſweeter alſo then the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie and the honie combe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.21.</note> How ſweet are the mercies of the Lord! and that my ſoule knoweth right well, which forgineth all mine iniquities,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2273:13"/>and healeth all mine infirmities, which redeemed my life from the graue,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.3, 4.</note> and crowneth me with mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi> And what ſhal I ſay of his iudgements? May we not ſee <hi>Sampſons</hi> riddle heerein expounded without the helpe of any Sphinx,
<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.14:</note> 
                     <hi>Out of the ſtrong com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſweetnes, and out of the lion the honie combe?</hi> O how ſweete are his corrections! as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious balme of Gilead, as caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes in phyſick, and not as pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments in hoſtilitie. O ſweet Sauiour, thou haſt well ſaid it, and we finde it true,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.29. Cant. 9.16.</note> Thy yoke is eaſie, and thy burthen is light; yea thou art wholly delectable.</p>
                  <p>O they bee bleſſed whoſ God is the Lord <hi>Iehoua:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The ſecuritie of thoſe vvhich haue taſted the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 84.5. Iſai. 48.21.</note> Bleſſed is the man whoſe ſtrength is in thee, and in whoſe heart are thy waies: His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe,</hi> when the wicked ſhall bee afraid of their owne ſhadow, and tremble like an Aſpin leafe at euery little blaſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2273:13"/>of winde or thunder-clap:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee that dwelleth vnder the ſhadow of the Almightie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 46.2.3.</note> his ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, though the earth be moued, and the waters of the ſea rage, and the mountaines ſhake at the ſurges of the ſame,</hi> their mindes are void of feare. And why?
<note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> 
                     <hi>There is a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whoſe ſtreames make glad the citie of God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.4.</note> Hee couereth them vnder his wings, and they are ſafe vnder his feathers. They know and are aſſured that <hi>all things ſhall worke together for the beſt to them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> that they are beloued of God,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.27. Iſai. 1.18.</note> their names written in heauen, and their (though crimſon) ſinnes waſhed in the blood of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lambe,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 7.14.</note> and that neither height, nor depth, nor death, nor life, nor any thing ſhall bee able to ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the loue of God which is in Chriſt Ieſus their Lord.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> The ful aſſurance whereof, when they hold in better tenour then they can hold any thing in this life by
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2273:14"/>ſeale, leaſe, writing, witneſſe, or any other way that law can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe; O how it glads their hearts and cheereth vp their vitall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits! What an heauenly comfort is it for them to meditate thus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with themſelues,
<note place="margin">Pſal.</note> that they <hi>ſhall ſee the good pleaſures of the Lord in the land of the liuing,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> and haue an houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heauens!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Stoope downe to this all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of wealth,
<note place="margin">Wicked men oft deſire his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and would giue a world for it.</note> pleaſure, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the world (in what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count or price ſoeuer they bee with worldly fooles:) there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a <hi>Balaam</hi> (were he well adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) but would giue them all for one quarter of an houres feeling of Gods louing kindnes &amp; ſweet countenance toward him.
<note place="margin">Numb. 23.10.</note> Sillie wretches, albeit they would ſeem to ſpend their daies in mirth, and with a light heart to paſſe away the time,
<note place="margin">Iob 21.13.</note> yet (God hee knoweth) with wearie ſighes and grones
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2273:14"/>that cannot be expreſſed, many a time their ſoules thus reaſon with themſelues: O how happie are they whoſe names are written in the booke of life! O that they might die the death of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and that their latter end might be like his! O what an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable treaſure is the peace of conſcience! yea and what they would giue for a taſte thereof? how many thouſand worlds, if it were in their power, for a part in Gods kingdome? But theſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are onely for the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromes friends,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.10.</note> theſe dainties are for the children; ſuch whelpes ſhall not bee ſuffered to taſte ſo much as of the crummes that fall from the childrens table.
<note place="margin">Mark. 7.27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>my ſeruants ſhall eate, and yee ſhall be hungrie;
<note place="margin">Only the godly feele &amp; enioy it.</note> my ſeruants ſhall drinke, and ye ſhal be thirsty; my ſeruants ſhall reioyce,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 65.13.14.</note> and ye ſhall be aſhamed; my ſeruants ſhall ſing for ioy of heart, and ye ſhall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2273:15"/>crie for ſorrow of heart, and howle for vexation of minde.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 4.32.</note> They haue another meate to eate which the world knoweth not; they haue another drinke to drinke, which others dreame not of, for their meate is of the tree of life,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.1.</note> and the Nectar which they ſup out of the ſweetnes of their gratious God is as <hi>a well of water ſpringing vp to euerlaſting life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 4.14. <hi>Gods ſeruice not grieuous to his.</hi>
                     </note> So that they feele that moſt delightfull, which to the wicked and vngodly is moſt irkeſome; they ſee and feele the ſeruice of the Lord to bee the chiefeſt freedome,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> becauſe the Lord is a plentifull rewarder of them that ſeeke him, they finde his yoke not cumberſome but ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.29.</note> and his burthen not heauie but light,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.8.</note> ſo that they are neither idle nor vnfruitfull in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.10.</note> but ready and prepared to euery good worke: when they haue taſted once <hi>of the good word of God,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.5.</note> and of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2273:15"/>powers of the world to come,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 4.34.</note> O then it is meate and drinke to them to do their fathers will,
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 119.110.</note> the precepts of the Lord are the very ioy of their heart,
<note place="margin">Deut. 12.18.</note> ſo that they cannot chuſe but reioice before the Lord in all that they ſet their hands vnto.</p>
                  <p>And albeit by reaſon of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of ſinne and rebellion of nature,
<note place="margin">The godly though much troubled vvith rebellion, yet vvith comfort proceed in the courſe of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> which ſtill ſticketh to the ribs euen of Gods deareſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the fleſh in them is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times rebellious againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; ſo that the good things which they would doe, oft times they leaue vndone,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.19.</note> and doe the euill things which they would not do; ſo that for grief hereof they break foorth into this complaint; <hi>O wretched men that we are,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 24.</note> who ſhall deliuer vs from this bodie of death!</hi> yet they ſhall haue this word of comfort fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their God,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.9.</note> 
                     <hi>my grace is ſufficient for you;</hi> though they ſinne, yet they haue an aduocate
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2273:16"/>with the Father,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.2.</note> Ieſus Chriſt the righteous,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.4.</note> who is the propitiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their ſinnes; though they fall, yet they ſhall riſe againe;
<note place="margin">Luke 22.31.32.</note> though that Satan deſire to ſift them like wheate, yet they ſhall not faile; though all the infernall power ſeeke their ouerthrow,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.18.</note> yet the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.
<note place="margin">Sweet helpes for the godly to grow in faith and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>What ſhould I here ſpeake of the ſweetneſſe of thoſe gratious helps which God doth giue vnto his children, to make them grow in faith and godlineſſe; his holie word to inſtruct them, his diuine inſpirations to illighten them, his ſweete Sacraments to nouriſh them, his often checks of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to recall them, his fatherly chaſtiſements to reclaime them, which though they be gall and wormewood to the wicked, yet are ſweete and gainfull to thoſe that feare our Lord. What a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit is it by prayer to come vnto
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2273:16"/>our God for whatſoeuer we haue need, that is good for vs, and may obtaine it? How comfortable is it to reade and to reuolue the booke of comfort?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1 2.3. Pſal. 1.9.</note> How heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a thing is it to be rapt vp as it were into heauen with heauenly meditations, to vſe Chriſtian co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119. part. 2</note> with our lips alwaies to be declaring the iudgements of the Lord, and to bee ſpeaking of the teſtimonies of our God, when we ſit in our houſe, or walk in our way, when wee lie downe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 11.19.</note> and when we riſe vp: O what a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure paſſing pleaſure is this, to haue the word of God dwell in vs <hi>plenteouſly in all wiſdome,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.16.</note> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and admoniſhing our ſelues mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in Pſalmes, hymnes, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſongs, ſinging, and making melodie to the Lord in our hearts?</hi> and to enioy the bleſſed commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, which none but Saints do vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, none but the elect ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enioy.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2273:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Glorious things are ſpoken of thee,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The priuiledges of the faithfull.</hi> Pſalm. 87.3.</note> thou citie of God: O how goodly are thy tents O Iacob, and thine habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, O Iſrael! As the vallies are they ſtretched forth, as gardens by the riuers ſide, as the Aloe trees which the Lord hath planted,
<note place="margin">Numb. 24.5.6.</note> and as the cedars beſides the waters.</hi> Why, <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is reuealed to them that feare him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gods ſecrets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to his children.</hi> Pſalm. 25.14.</note> and his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant to giue them vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Seemeth it a ſmall thing vnto you,
<note place="margin">They are Gods ſeruants.</note> O ye ſeruants of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerliuing God, to be admitted to the priuy chamber of the King of heauen, and to be of his counſell? To be the Chancellor, Treaſurer, or Secretary to an earthly prince, wee ſee it a matter of great ſtate and much reſpected honour: but what is that to this honor (which the very pooreſt and meaneſt of Gods ſeruants are aduanced vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) to bee the ſeruants vnto the King of Kings, &amp; Lord of Lords, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which title the Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2273:17"/>haue no greater,
<note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note> and which the greateſt part of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Kings and Emperours could neuer attaine vnto? But what doe I ſpeake of ſeruants?
<note place="margin">They are Christs friends.</note> Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſetteth foorth your eſtate to be yet more glorious, when hee ſaith, <hi>I haue not called you ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.15.</note> but friends,</hi> to whom <hi>I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated my ſecrets and minde,</hi> vnto which a ſeruant is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly admitted.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> And if this bee not yet enough, behold your God hath adopted you to be his ſonnes and heires, yea fellowe heires with Chriſt himſelfe, then which, what greater priuiledge, what greater prerogatiue can there be? Heare, I pray you, O ye citizens of heauen; may it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſeeme a ſmall thing to be a people ſeparated vnto God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the multitude of men,
<note place="margin">Exod. 19.5.</note> to be the moſt pretious of all the earth to him, though all the earth be his? Is it a ſmall thing to be <hi>a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2273:18"/>choſen generation,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.9.</note> a royall Priest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, an holy nation, a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?</hi> See, and with thankfull harts acknowledge this your priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>That you are come to the mount Sion, the citie of the liuing God, the celeſtiall Ieruſalem, and to the companie of innumerable An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22, 23, 24.</note> and to the congregation of the firſt borne which are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and to God the iudge of all, and to the ſpirits of iust and perfect me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to Ieſus the mediatour of the new Teſtament,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.24.</note> and to the blood of ſprinkling that ſpeaketh better things then the blood of Abel.</hi> Cheere vp then your drooping ſpirits, and take heart at this your happineſſe, howſoeuer the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Belial</hi> ſpeake euill of you, and yee are eſteemed as the filth of the world,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.13.</note> and as the offcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of all things vnto this day: For howſoeuer <hi>Iſmael</hi> ſcoffe at <hi>Iſaac;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 21.9.</note> and the children of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman perſecute the children of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2273:18"/>the free woman,
<note place="margin">Galat. 4.29. Ieremy. Pſal i.e.</note> ſmiting them with their tongue, and ſhooting out their arrowes againſt them, euen bitter words, yet, wel I wot, in the midſt of their bitter ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, when the worme of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence gnaweth on their ſoules, <hi>in thoſe daies ſhall tenne men take hold out of all languages of the nations,
<note place="margin">Zach 8.23.</note> euen take hold of the skirt of him that is a Christian, and ſay, Wee would goe with you, for wee haue heard that God is with you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea the Lord is with vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>God is alwaies with his, and hath a ſpeciall care of them.</hi> Pſal. 46.7. Pſal. 34.15. Verſ. 18. Verſ. 7. Pſal. 30.6.7.</note> 
                     <hi>The God of Iacob is our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: The eyes of the Lord are vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the righteous, and his eares are open to their crie: the Lord is neere vnto them that are of a contrire heart: The Angell of the Lord pitcheth his tents round about them that feare him, and deliuereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> He is their ſhelter from tempeſts and ſtormes of troubles; he kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth them ſafe vnder his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as the henne doth the chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2273:19"/>vnder her wing,
<note place="margin">Luke 13.34. Deut. 32.10.</note> yea hee keepeth them as the apple of his eye.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.10.</note> 
                     <hi>The lions doe lacke and ſuffer hunger, but they which ſeeke the Lord ſhall want nothing that is good:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.1. Rom. 8.31.</note> God is their ſhepheard, what can they want? Hee is on their ſide, who can bee againſt them?
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> He honoreth them, whoſe diſgracing of them can hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? In euery eſtate he ſaueth and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holdeth them by his prouidence,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.7.</note> what miſerie can befal them? <hi>God is their God for euer and euer,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 48.14.</note> euen their guide vnto the death.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 149.9.</note> This ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhall be to all his Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And albeit heere it pleaſe the Lord for a while to trie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with affliction,
<note place="margin">Affliction taketh away nothing of Gods ſweetnes.</note> and to chaſtize them with his correction, to mingle their wine with Aloes, and to ſend much bitternes into their cup: <hi>Yet,</hi> howſoeuer it be, <hi>God is good to Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.1. Malach. 3.6. 1. Cor. 4.9.</note> euen to thoſe that are pure in heart:</hi> Ye ſonnes of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> ſhall not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed, though
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2273:19"/>you are in diſtreſſe, yet you ſhall not be forſaken:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Heauineſſe may endure for a night, but ioy will come in the morning:
<note place="margin">Hoſea 6.2.</note> After two daies he will reuiue vs, and the third day hee will raiſe vs vp againe.</hi> Thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements, O Lord, are like the pretious balme of Gilead,
<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> which will not breake but ſupple our heads: How many thouſands of thy Saints may ſay, It was good for vs,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.71.</note> yea exceeding good that wee were in troubles? Thou, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 3.11.</note> doeſt loue thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou chaſteneſt: and <hi>albeit no chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for the preſent ſeemeth to bee ioyous, but grieuous; yet afterward it bringeth the quiet fruite of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes vnto them which are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by exerciſed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> For <hi>the afflictions of this world are not worthie of the ioyes</hi> that ſucceed them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28. Heb. 12.6.</note> and <hi>All things</hi> (euen afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s themſelues) <hi>turne to the beſt to them that feare</hi> God, and are ſignes that they are beloued of God. Behold the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2273:20"/>childe of God whoſe affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are the greateſt, and marke and behold his end,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> for the end of that man is peace. And though God for a while doe ſeeme to hide away his face, ſo that the godlie ſoule goeth heauie and mourning all the day long;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 30.11.</note> yet God will turne their mourning into ioy;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 56.8.</note> he will looſe their ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and gird them with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes;
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note> he will put their teares into his bottle, and in all theſe things in the end they ſhall bee more then conquerors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O Lord of hoſts how amiable are thy tabernacles!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The boldnes of the faithfull in their prayers.</hi> Pſal. 84.1.</note> how ful of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes! Why Lord, wee ſee here vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth how hard a matter it is to haue acceſſe to the great men of this world, which differ from our ſelues not in ſtuffe, but in vſe, and that for a while; and to an earthly Prince but at ſometime and for ſome one pleaſure is few mens caſes to obtain an entrance,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2273:20"/>when as we may boldly preſſe in to the portall of thy priuie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and with confidence breake our mindes, lay open our griefe,
<note place="margin">Mark. 11.24.</note> preferre our ſuite, and commune familiarly with thee, as with a friend, when wee will, as often as we will, thou neuer being wearie of vs, neuer taking ſcorne nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting vs: yea thou doeſt inuite vs to come vnto thee, and art more neere to heare then wee to aske: and although in our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers there are manifold infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and wee know not how to pray as wee ought, and are ſoone wearie and cold in praying, yet the ſpirit helpeth our infirmities, yea the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for vs with ſighes which cannot be expreſſed.
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> O when was there any that could ſay he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in vaine, if his prayer were it ſelfe not vaine? who can repent, or bethinke any minute of time herein ſpent? <hi>This is the aſſurance
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2273:21"/>which wee haue of him,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.14.</note> that if wee aske any thing according to his will, hee heareth vs.</hi> And albeit God doth not preſently grant our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and ſometimes ſeemeth to defer the hearing of the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; yet is his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe heerein exceeding large to them that feare him. All this tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to the beſt for them; their faith being exerciſed, their hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after grace, more heereby ſtrengthened and encreaſed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſtirred vp the better to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme of the graces of God whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues more thankfull for them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſo is wiſe will obſerue theſe things,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.43.</note> that he may vnderſtand the louing kindnes of the Lord: for his mercie is great vnto the heauens,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 108.4.</note> and his trueth reacheth vnto the clouds.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 145.9. &amp; 15.</note> The Lord is good to all, and his mercies are ouer all his workes. The eyes of all wait vpon him, and he giueth them their foode: Hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2273:21"/>the Sun to ſhine vpon the euill and the good,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.45.</note> and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt.
<note place="margin">Luke 6.35.</note> He is kind euen to the vnkind;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 87.2.</note> yet <hi>the Lord loueth the gates of Sion aboue all the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of Iacob.</hi> He hath liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouided for them aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, both here in this life, and in the life to come: he hath laid vp for them his ſweeteſt ſweetes. A taſte whereof though they haue here in this world, (and that ſo glorious as that it is ineffable) yet the full fruition is reſerued for them in a better world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall bee repleniſhed with the ſweetnes of his preſence, and ſee him face to face, <hi>at whoſe right hand are fulneſſe of pleaſures for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If in this life only we had hope in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.19.</note> we were of all men the moſt miſerable</hi> (and yet in this life alſo our ſweetnes we feele in God is incomprehenſible) but there is reſerued for vs a better life, and in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2273:22"/>that life a richer ſweetnes, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand degrees more then tongue can ſpeake,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> or heart can thinke. <hi>Wee know this that when this earthly houſe of our tabernacle ſhall be deſtroyed, wee haue a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not made with hands,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.2.</note> but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the heauens: therefore wee ſigh, deſiring to be clothed with our houſe from heauen:</hi> There we haue in ſtore laid vp for vs <hi>an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance immortall and vndefiled that fadeth not away,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4. and 18.19.</note> but is reſerued in heauen</hi> for vs, bought and purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not with gold and ſiluer, but with a farre more excellent price, euen with the pretious blood of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p>Had I the tongue of men and Angels, yet were I not able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the leaſt glimmering light or taſte of this reſerued ſweetnes. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe rapt vp into the third heauen,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> and hauing heard things that were not to bee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſeene ſights not to bee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2273:22"/>ſpecified, paſſeth them ouer with this preterition; The ſweetneſſe reſerued for Gods children in heauen is ſuch,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> as no <hi>eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, neither is the hart of man able to conceiue.</hi> O happie and thrice happie they that ſhall one day feele and ſee and taſte the ſame. Mine heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyceth, my ſoule leapeth, my tongue and penne exult, to think vpon the ſweetneſſe of it, and to thinke vpon mine owne happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who am right well aſſured that one day I ſhall enioy the ſame: O when ſhall I come to appeare before the Lord in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? <hi>My ſoule longeth,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> yea and fainteth for theſe courts of the Lord; my heart and my fleſh reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth in the liuing Lord: for I am ſure that my redeemer liueth, and though after my skinne wormes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy this carcaſe of mine, yet ſhall I ſee God in my fleſh,
<note place="margin">Iob 19.25.26.27.</note> whom I my ſelf ſhall ſee, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and none other for me, though my
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2273:23"/>reines be conſumed within mee.</hi> O happie time (it ioyes my very hart to thinke of it before it comes) where this poore ſoule of mine bidding a farewell to my bodie for a while, ſhall be carried with no meaner attendants on it, then a guard of angels into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, there to take poſſeſſion of a kingdome, vpon the receit whereof it ſhall enter the fee ſimple of life, which it ſhall neuer loſe: O what a glorious welcom and meeting ſhall it haue with al the companie of celeſtiall euer bleſſed ſpirits, with Angels, and Archangels, Cherubims and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphims, principalities, powers, thrones and dominations, with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob,</hi> and all the holy Patriarks, with <hi>Iſay, Ieremie, Hoſea,</hi> and all the famous Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, with <hi>Peter, Iames</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn.</hi> and all the reſt of Chriſts Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, yea with the whole compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Martyrs, Innocents, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Saints of God, with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2273:23"/>them together, to enioy the higheſt degree of the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Saints for euermore! Why, my ſoule, there is wonderfull ſweetneſſe laid vp in heauen for thee, the time is comming when thou ſhalt enter into thy glorie; where is a citie, and the gates of it are pearle, and the ſtreetes of it gold, and the walles of it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones, and the Temple in it the Almighty God, and the light of it the Lambe, and the veſſels to it the Kings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth; where is a riuer, &amp; the ſpring of it is the throne of God, and the water of it Cryſtall, and the bankes of it ſet about with the trees of life; where there is a banquet, and the cheere is ioy, the exerciſe ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the dittie <hi>Halleluiahs,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ 4.</note> the Quire Angels, where all teares ſhall be wiped away from thine eyes, <hi>and there ſhall be no more death, nor ſorrow, nor crying, nor paine; where</hi> there is infinite ioy and mirth without ſadnes, health
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2273:24"/>without ſicknes, light without darknes, felicitic without abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all goodneſſe without any euill; where youth floriſheth that neuer waxeth old, life laſteth that neuer endeth, beautie that neuer fadeth, loue that neuer cooleth, health that neuer diminiſheth, ioy that neuer ceaſeth; where ſorrow is neuer felt, complaint is neuer heard, matter of ſadnes is neuer ſeene, where in the ſame inſtant I ſhall be rauiſhed with ſeeing; ſatisfied with enioying, ſecured for retaining. O ſweeteſt happineſſe, how doe I long for to be filled with thee! how doe I hunger and thirſt after thee! But euen heere alreadie I haue more then either I could deſire or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: I will not leaue my ſolace in this world for the worldlings heauen, a dramme of Chriſtian comfort is better then a pound of earthly ioy, I had rather enioy a taſte of this, then to liue at rack &amp; manger in any other happineſſe.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2273:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>True delight:</hi> Or, THE WORLDS Farewell, and Chriſts <hi>Welcome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head type="sub">TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. GEORGE BAINARD, and Miſtris BAINARD his Wife.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing begunne to make theſe my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Meditations publique, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them vnder the protection of many their beſt well-willers to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2273:25"/>ſee the world, I ſhould much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my ſelfe (Worſhipfull and most eſpeciall benefactors) if I ſhould forget your names in theſe my multiplied dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. There is no man liuing who may claime that intereſt in mee, or challenge my very beſt endeuours in that meaſure as your ſelues, who may iustly ſay to me, as</hi> Paul <hi>did to</hi> Philemon;
<note place="margin">Philem. 19.</note> Thou oweſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs euen thine owne ſelfe. <hi>For beſides that, your houſe hath been to me as the houſe of</hi> One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphorus <hi>was to</hi> Paul,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.16.</note> 
                     <hi>euen this alſo that I my ſelfe haue an houſe to dwell in, and a pastoral charge to labour in, I may impute it vnto your ſelues, as principall meanes, raiſed vp by God, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it for me.
<note place="margin">Iob 31.20.</note> The loines of me and mine may bleſſe you, becauſe by your meanes wee are cloathed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2273:25"/>with a fleece. I haue nothing to returne vnto you for your ſo great paines, but theſe few home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie papers, the poore preſent of an euer remaining debtor; I would they were as worthie of any reſpect with you, as in many reſpects they doe belong vnto you. My ſoule perſwadeth it ſelfe that you both are of the number of thoſe,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.4.</note> who haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the ſeale of the lion of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,
<note place="margin">Galat. 6.16.</note> that long ſince the world hath bin crucified vnto you, and you vnto the world, &amp; that you haue propoſed Chriſt Ieſus to your ſelues the onely gaine:
<note place="margin">Philip 1.21.</note> I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſend not vnto you this fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well which I haue ſung vnto the world to perſwade you, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to encourage you:
<note place="margin">Phil. 1.6.</note> He that hath begun a good worke in you, will performe it and encreaſe it
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2273:26"/>more and more:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 9.</note> And this I pray that your loue may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound yet more and more in knowledge, and in all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> that yee may diſcerne things that differ, and may be pure and without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence vntil the day of Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in the Lord Ieſus, <hi>G. W.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2273:26"/>
                  <head>True delight.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PHILIP. 3.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Yea doubtleſſe I thinke al things but loſſe for the excellent knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord, for whom I haue counted all things loſſe, and doe iudge them to bee dung, that I might win Chriſt.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe deſperate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed times, wherein men are ſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallie drunken with their owne conceits, to ſee how fondly conceited the ſelfe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing humors of <hi>Adams</hi> children are, I know not whether with <hi>Democritus</hi> I might laugh; or with <hi>Heraclitus</hi> I ſhould rather weepe. One maketh his heauen
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2273:27"/>of the droſſe and rubbiſh of the earth,
<note place="margin">The diuers vaine delights of the moſt part.</note> his muckie wealth, and ſo becommeth a ſlaue vnto his ſlaue. Another maketh his bellie his god,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.19.</note> repoſing his chiefeſt felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in pampering of his guts. An other toadlike ſwelleth with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, ſeeking after vainglorious honour, as children after feathers flying in the aire, toſſed about hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and thither with the blaſt of manie mouthes. Another like <hi>Narciſſus</hi> becomes inamoured on Natures dowrie his beautie,
<note place="margin">Ouid Metam.</note> or Natures ſhame his cloathes. An other ſeateth his chiefeſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in a Dog, another in a Kite, another in a Horſe, another in a ſmoake euaporating weede: The better ſort (at leaſt wiſe to mans eyes the more ingenious) either like <hi>Pharao</hi> glorie in their wit,
<note place="margin">Exod. 1.10. 2. Sam. 16.23. Act. 24.1.2.3.</note> or like <hi>Achitophel</hi> in their policie, or like <hi>Tertullus</hi> in their eloquence, or like Babels Monarch,
<note place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note> proud <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> in their buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2273:27"/>or like <hi>Zenacherib</hi> in their greatnes,
<note place="margin">1. King. 18. 1. Sam. 17.5. 1. King. 12.8.</note> or like <hi>Goliah</hi> in their ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, or like <hi>Rehoboam</hi> in their birth,
<note place="margin">Iohn 7.48.</note> or like the Phariſies in their knowledge,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 9.3.</note> or like the Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites in their cunning, or elſe in ſome accidentall gifts (as we call them) of Nature, wit or fortune.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ariſt. Ethic. lib.</hi> 2</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>All theſe with a thouſand more men pleaſing pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights,
<note place="margin">A cenſure vpon the former de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</note> (which worldlings value at ſo high a rate) were they tenne thouſand thouſand times better then they are, I ſee no reaſon why I ſhould count them any better, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apparant loſſes, bitter ſweets, gliding ſhadowes, gaudie toyes, yea but chips, dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffe, and dung, in compariſon of thoſe ineſtimable treaſures and delights which are to be had in Chriſt Ieſus. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that, if wee would compare them together, they are paſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.11.</note> and as high as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is aboue the earth, ſo &amp; much more excellent is Chriſt Ieſus vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2273:28"/>the ſoule, then any earthly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace can be in the world: what reaſon is there, if we had no hope at all of heauen, or expectation of greater happineſſe in another world, why wee ſhould ſet our hearts or fixe our affections vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any thing here in this world? what gaine can I make? what contentment is it poſſible that I ſhuld find in any of theſe things, whoſe goodneſſe is but in ſhew,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 40.6.</note> whoſe pleaſure is but in opinion, whoſe glorie is but as a flower of the field, with which the minde is neuer ſatisfied, the affection neuer quieted, the appetite neuer contented? but if we had the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of them all together, we ſhould prooue his teſtimonie of them all to be moſt true, who had experience in them more then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.2.</note> They are <hi>vanities of vanities, vanitie of vanities,</hi> nothing elſe but vanitie.</p>
                  <p>I cannot chuſe but wonder at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2273:28"/>the Anakims of our age,
<note place="margin">Nobilitie.</note> that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie their heads aloft, and ſpeake with a preſumptuous mouth,
<note place="margin">Numb. 13.29. Pſal. 78.5.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their blood, and bragge of their Nobilitie; when as I ſee that Nobilitie it ſelfe (bee it neuer ſo pretious a pearle in the worlds eye) is but a name without a nature, a ſhadow without a ſubſtance; make the beſt of it, it is but the daughter of rottenneſſe,
<note place="margin">Iob 17.14.</note> and the ſiſter of wormes: the glorie of it is but a nominall credit begged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead men, a trifling title raked from their graues, who are long ſince diſſolued into duſt and aſhes.
<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> No blood ſo noble but is attainted with <hi>Adams</hi> ſhame, and when the pedigree is fet as farre as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly it may bee,
<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> may ſhake hands with rich <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues,</hi> and call him coſin.</p>
                  <p>Me thinks it is but madnes and a fretting phrenſie which I ſee in many, whoſe onely marke they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2273:29"/>aime at is their honour;
<note place="margin">Hanor.</note> when as Honour what art thou, but a bubble quickly vp, &amp; on a ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down? a very blazing ſtarre drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the minde with preſaging ruine. O yee ambitious aſpiring ſpirits, what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſee in Honor that you ſhould affect it? when it moſt frowneth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her ſeruants, and caſteth downe thoſe whom it lifteth vp? The greateſt honors are expoſed to the moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous aduentures &amp; enuying cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: Dignities doe but digge thorow the heart with cares; Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices are but ſeruices,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.</note> and <hi>man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the greateſt honor may be compared to the beasts that periſh;</hi> yea you Demigods ſhall turne to duſt as well as other.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.7</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And as for Beautie,
<note place="margin">Beautie is but loſſe.</note> fooles they are, in my conceit, which pleaſe themſelues with it, when they ſee it in themſelues; or endanger their ſoules for it, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it in others: For, <hi>vaine is
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2273:29"/>beautie,
<note place="margin">Prouerb. 31.</note> and deceiueable is the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the countenance.</hi> The fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt face in the world raſe it ouer but with a little ſcratch, and the grace thereof is gone; let an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue viſit it, the flower thereof is decaied; let the ſoule depart from it but halfe an houre, and this louely face is pale, grimme and gaſtly to looke vpon. O ye glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Ladies and dainty Dames, whoſe glorie is your beautie, and whoſe labor is your vanitic; that face of yours, vpon which the winde may not blow, nor the Sun ſhine, nor the ayre breathe; thoſe vermillion cheeks ſo ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked either with natures ſanguine bluſh, or elſe bedaubed with counterfeit colours, borrowed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a diſſembling art: That bodie ſo trimly adorned with rich ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell &amp; coſtly ornaments, what are they but the food of vermine and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crawling place of wormes, the inheritrix of rottenneſſe and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2273:30"/>ſubiect of putrifaction? The time is comming, yea the time com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth on apace when the <hi>keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.3.4.5</note> and the ſtrong men ſhall bow themſelues, and the grinders ceaſe, becauſe they are few, and they waxe darke that looke out at the windowes, and duſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to duſt againe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What madneſſe then is it to glorie in our carcaſe,
<note place="margin">Apparell.</note> or to take pride in our bodies veſtments? as if a malefactor ſhould be proud of his halter, or a begger bragge of his rags, the very enſignes of his baſe eſtate. The apparell that we weare, wee are beholding to the dumb and vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for it; worſe then beaſts we, if wee take pride in that which beaſts haue worne before vs. For our Wollen we are beholding to the ſillie Sheepe; for our Linnen, to a Weede; for our Silkes, vnto the very excrements of Wormes; our Gold is but the dregs of the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2273:30"/>earth, our pretious pearles wee borrow from the fiſhes: and bee our cloathing neuer ſo coſtly,
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.29.</note> yet none, no not <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe in all his royaltie, is cloathed like the lilies of the field.</p>
                  <p>There is an euill ſicknes vnder the Sun,
<note place="margin">Riches.</note> and it is much amongſt men; to compaſſe ſea and land for hoarding vp of wealth;
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 6.1.</note> and it is reckoned now adaies the only gaine to fill their coffers with mony treaſure, the only paradiſe to looke vpon theſe falſely tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med goods:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sueton. in vita Calig. cap.</hi> 42.</note> I ſee no ſuch ſolace in it. Me thinkes <hi>Caligula</hi> was but a foole when he ſo delighted to touch and handle mony, that lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great heapes of gold in a ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious place, hee might tread on it bare foote, and tumble it vp and downe: and I pitie their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous practiſe and toiling life, who thirſt ſo greedily, and ſcrape together ſo eagerly, &amp; lock vp ſo carefully theſe ſo truly called <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2273:31"/>riches.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.17.</note> O you mony ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and wealth admirers, your riches are not as the water of life alwaies flowing, but as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brooks of Arabia, which are then moſt drie when one ſhould moſt need them for water! They be like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Spider webs, which when they waxe great, are ſwept away with a beſome, either they periſh from you, or you from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Why then doe you caſt your eyes vpon that which is nothing? for <hi>riches betaketh her ſelfe to her wings like an Eagle:
<note place="margin">Prou. 23.5. Pſal. 49.17.</note> The rich man ſhall take nothing away with him when hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<note place="margin">Iob 27.19.</note> neither ſhall his pompe follow him: The rich man ſleeps, and when he openeth his eyes there is nothing:</hi> whiles worldly miſers dreame of multiplying their wealth,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.20.</note> poore fooles, death comes and makes a diuorce between them and their goods,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.15.</note> and they muſt <hi>returne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as they came,</hi> and <hi>what profit then hath the rich man that he hath
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2273:31"/>laboured for the winde?</hi> And yet wee ſee there is no end of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of this, as riches are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, ſo likewiſe are they inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable. <hi>There is one alone,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.8.</note> &amp; there is not a ſecond, which hath neither ſonne nor brother, yet is there no end of all his trauell, neither can his eye be ſatisfied with riches, neither doth he thinke, for whom doe I tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and defraud my ſoule of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? This alſo is vanitie;</hi> a man may ſweare it is but vanitie: mad <hi>Oreſtes</hi> might well iudge ſuch a miſerable man much more mad, that ſtandeth thus like <hi>Tantalus</hi> in the ſtygean lake,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Horat. ſat.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 1</note> and like the drudging Indians which toile in the golden mines, but enioy none of the Ore.</p>
                  <p>By how much the more may wee ſtill admire the follie or the phrenſie rather of thoſe,
<note place="margin">Purchaſings and poſſeſſions.</note> whoſe ſoule, as if it were made of earth,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.8.</note> is euer plotting to ioyne houſe to houſe &amp; land to land? and though
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2273:32"/>their inheritance ſtretch to the plaine of Iordan,
<note place="margin">Numb. 1.14.</note> yet are alwaies with vnquiet mindes ſtirring and ſtriuing to inlarge their demains: Doubtleſſe it is but loſt labour that <hi>they riſe vp early and ſo late take reſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note> whiles Gods beloued take their quiet ſleepe: for in the middeſt of all their wealth, their <hi>ſoules ſhall be taken from them,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.20.</note> and then whoſe ſhall theſe things bee?</hi> yea though like another <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> a man could ſtretch his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt, and from the North vnto the South, yet within ſhort ſpace a ſeuen foote of ground, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, will be the moſt that hee can claime to be his owne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet they thinke their houſes ſhall endure for euer,
<note place="margin">Buildings.</note>
                        <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.11.</note> euen from genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to generation, and call their lands by their names:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.18.</note> therefore like to <hi>Abſalom</hi> they build Pyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mides to keepe their name in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and glorie not a
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2273:32"/>little in their coſtly buildings, as if they ſhould remaine for euer; This alſo is meere vanitie and vexation of ſpirit.
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.26.</note> For what are all the ſumptuous buildings in the world but heapes of ſtones peeced &amp; patched together with lime and morter, which like to ſwallowes neſts in winter do fall downe of themſelues,
<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in epist. ad Coloſſ.</note> and which all conſuming time at laſt diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth,
<note place="margin">Luke 19.44.</note> leauing not ſo much as one ſtone vpon another?</p>
                  <p>I come now to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> garden of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donis,</hi> variety of pleaſures,
<note place="margin">Pleaſure.</note> which the world maketh her garden of Eden: the flowers which therein grow are the vaine plants of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and delight; which albeit they make a glorious ſhew to the eyes, yet is their roote bitternes, their gloſſe vanitie, and their fruite poiſon. Beautifull obiects which delight the eyes, ſweete ſounds that pleaſe the eares, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant ſmels that affect the noſe,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2273:33"/>any other accidents that pleaſe the other ſenſes, what they are, when they are euen at the beſt, let him,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.3. <hi>I ſought, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> let him that drew the threed of delight, and ſtretched the webbe of pleaſures on the largeſt tenter of varietie, come foorth and ſpeake.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I ſaid in mine heart,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Salomons pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batum eſt.</hi> Eccleſ. 2.1.</note> (ſaith hee the wiſeſt Sceptick) <hi>Goe to now I will prooue thee with ioy, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take thou pleaſure in pleaſant things.</hi> But what followed? <hi>I ſaid of laughter,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioy &amp; laughter.</hi> Verſe 2.</note> thou art mad, and of ioy, what is it that thou doeſt? laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is mingled with ſorrow,
<note place="margin">Prou. 14.</note> and mourning enſueth at the end of mirth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 4. <hi>Houſes. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyarde. Gardens. Orchards.</hi> Verſ. 5. <hi>Ceſternes.</hi> Verſ. 6. <hi>Seruants. Children. Demaines.</hi>
                     </note> Well, he goeth on: <hi>I haue made my great workes, I haue built me houſes, I haue planted me vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, I haue made me gardens and orchards, and planted in them trees of all fruite, I haue made me ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes of water,</hi> to water there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the woods that grow with trees, <hi>I haue gotten ſeruants and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2273:33"/>maids,
<note place="margin">Verſ 7. <hi>Flocks. Cattell.</hi>
                        </note> and had children borne in the houſe alſo I had great poſſeſſions of Beoues and Sheepe aboue all that were before me in Ieruſalem,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 8. <hi>Siluer. Gold. Treaſure. Muſicke.</hi>
                        </note> I haue gathered vnto mee alſo ſiluer and gold, and the chief treaſure of kings and prouinces, I haue prouided mee menſingers and womenſingers; and the delights of the ſonnes of men: whatſoeuer mine eies deſired I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held it not from them,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> I withdrew not mine heart from any ioy. Then I looked on all the workes that mine hands had wrought, and on the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that I laboured to doe,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 11.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all is vanitie and vexation of ſpirit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If thou <hi>Salomon</hi> out of thy ſo deare bought experience doeſt giue no better commendation of this world and theſe world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treaſures; ſurely, I ſee no cauſe why I ſhould affect them, or any of them, for my ſelfe, nor enuie them in others. No, no, I rather pitie them, that dote ſo much on
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2273:34"/>theſe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> and to enioy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon, take more paines, alas, then I can doe for true delight. Well, well, I ſee that all things here are full of vanitie, man cannot vtter it,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.8.</note> 
                     <hi>the eye is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the eare fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with hearing.</hi> A figge then for the world, I haue done with it, I ſee nothing worthie my loue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, I will thinke of them as they bee, and neuer ſet my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to them as the center of my hope.</p>
                  <p>Now am I in the prime of my youth,
<note place="margin">Youth.</note> neither haue mine eyes as yet ſeene (by two degrees) three decades of yeeres: ſhall I reioyce in this my youth,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.9.</note> becauſe I am but yet in my youth, in the flower and ſpring time of mine age? No, no,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">10.</note>I know that Childhood and youth are altogether vanitie; I count this al but loſſe, ſeeing that this age is prone to fill my bones with ſinne,
<note place="margin">Iob 20.11.</note> and to carrie the fire
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2273:34"/>and fuell of iniquitie in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome: and therefore with <hi>Dauid</hi> much more iuſtly may I pray,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 25.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the ſinnes of my youth, nor my rebellions:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 31.19.</note> for I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and confounded becauſe I doe beare the reproch of my youth.</hi> The ſtrength,
<note place="margin">Strength and agilitie.</note> nimblenes and agilitie of youth (which ſome doe glorie in) I count likewiſe but as loſſe: for the <hi>ſtrong man</hi> may <hi>not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in his ſtrength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. 9.23. Iudg. 16.</note> and <hi>Sampſons</hi> ſtrength pulled downe the houſe on his owne head; and let a man bee neuer ſo ſtrong, yet the time will ſoone approch,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.3.</note> 
                     <hi>when the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the houſe ſhall tremble, and the ſtrong men bow themſelues:</hi> The Lord alone is my ſtrength,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 27. Ephel. 6.</note> and my deſire is that I may bee ſtrong in him, and in the power of his might. Of all the tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefits in this life beſtowed on vs,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Health. Menander.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> there is none more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then Health; and this by the gratious goodneſſe of my good
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2273:35"/>God toward me I doe enioy, as much, I thinke, as any; yet can I not reioyce in this, I count it but a loſſe: for well I know, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou, Lord, doeſt begin to cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe man,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 39.11.</note> then health and all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume away like a moath fretting a garment. The Moone is not more variable in his changing, nor the ſea in her ebbing, then man in the change of his eſtate. Long life I neuer looke for,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Long life.</hi> Gen. 47.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Few and euill haue hitherto bin the daies of my pilgrimage;</hi> and were I ſure of long life, I ſhould be ſo much the more ſorrie for it: for what is length of life, but as to a ſick and pained ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a long winters night? the longer I liue the more I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the ſcore of my ſinnes. I know that whiles I am <hi>heere at home in the body,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.6. Philip. 1.23.</note> I am <hi>abſent from the Lord; I deſire therefore to be diſſolued and to bee with Chriſt.</hi> Proſperitie,
<note place="margin">Proſperitie.</note> if it ſhine vpon me as well as others, I ſee no cauſe why
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2273:35"/>I ſhould much eſteeme it:
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.45.</note> for the iuſt God <hi>maketh his Sunne to ariſe on the euill and the good, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth raine on the iuſt and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 27.39.</note> And wee ſee that <hi>Eſau</hi> hath the fatnes of the earth for his dwelling place, watered with the dew of heauen as well as <hi>Iacob.</hi> As for frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip,
<note place="margin">Friends.</note> I could co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend it, if I could know where to finde a faithfull friend:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.4.</note> 
                     <hi>But let euery one take heed of his neighbour, and not truſt in any brother: for euery brother will vſe deceit, and euerie friend will deale deceitfully.</hi> How many be there who (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ingeniouſly doth of himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) may complaine of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>O nimis inimica amicitia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt. Confeſ. lib.</hi> 2.</note> how dangerous a thing it is that they haue bin linkt in friendſhip? Single life I finde vncomfortable,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Single life. Mariage. Children.</hi> Pſal. 127.3.</note> and mariage full of trouble. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> indeed <hi>are the inheritance of the Lord, and the fruit of the womb is his reward,</hi> and by experience I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2273:36"/>finde it an extraordinarie fauour to haue them <hi>like oliue branches about our table;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 128.3.</note> yet the gaine of this I ſee it is but loſſe: for how can I tell whether my <hi>Beniamin</hi> will prooue <hi>Benonie,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 35.18. Ruth. 1.20.</note> or my <hi>Nao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi</hi> will be <hi>Mara</hi> vnto me? If they proue towardly Impes, yet is the future hope of them doubtfull, the comfort variable, the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall care moſt certaine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. Surely then all the world is vanitie; lay all the pleaſures of it in the ballance, and they ſhall be found lighter then vanitie it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 62.9.</note> And what ioy can I haue in any of theſe things, whiles I walk here in this vale of teares?</p>
                  <p>Learning I reuerence,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Learning.</hi> 1. Cor. 8.1.</note> but not adore: for <hi>knowledge puffeth vp,</hi> making men to ſwell like a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die bladder:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.18.</note> 
                     <hi>He that encreaſeth knowledge, encreaſeth ſorrow:</hi> and wel I know, that vnleſſe it be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, it is like <hi>Vriahs</hi> letter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe, and be a man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2273:36"/>ſo well skild in all Arts and Sciences, yet muſt he needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe (as one of the learnedeſt in that kinde doth) <hi>Hoc vnum ſcio,
<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> me nihil ſcire: Onely this I know, that I know nothing.</hi> Wit I like,
<note place="margin">Wit and policie.</note> but not extoll; policie I comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but cannot deifie. For if we take the waight of mans wit in ciuill things,
<note place="margin">Dan. 5.</note> it will be found like <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar</hi> too light: but lay his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall vnderſtanding vpon the ballance with ſpirituall things, and it ſhall be found lighter then vanitie it ſelfe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 26.</note> Doth not wit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times beguile it ſelfe, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies proue ſnares to intrap the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues withall? There is one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that catcheth the wiſe in their own craftines,
<note place="margin">Iob 5.13. 1. Cor. 3.19.</note> and the Lord knoweth that the thoughts of the wiſeſt are but vaine.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.11.</note> I ſee ſome reioyce in their memorie,
<note place="margin">Memorie.</note> me thinks it proueth but a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſeruant, retaining thoſe things which ſhe ſhould reiect, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecting
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2273:37"/>thoſe things which ſhee ſhould retaine; like the ſieue that holdeth faſt the courſe bran, but lets the fine flower fall away. They are without iudgement,
<note place="margin">Iudgement.</note> in my conceit, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boaſt ſo much of their owne iudgement, when hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane knowledge is but opinion, and the iudgement of the moſt expert prooues many times but a vaine Idaea of idle ſpeculations.</p>
                  <p>If I ſhould reckon vp all this worlds vanities, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by worldlings are hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted after as the onely treaſures, I ſhould take in hand an endleſſe taske, ſeeing of the ſame there is no end: O wretched world, what art thou, but an arke of trauell, a ſchoole of vanities, a ſeate of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, a labyrinth of errors? what is here in the world that ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue mine heart to be ſet vpon it? If the Diuell ſhould carrie me to the toppe of a mountaine,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.8.</note> and ſhew me all the kingdoms of the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2273:37"/>earth, and all the glorie of them, if hee ſhould offer, or could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the proffer of them all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me; what could from thence bee preſented to mine eyes, but falſe delights, true aſperitie, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſorrow, vncertain pleaſures, trauelſome labour, fearfull reſt? Shall my ſoule ſtoope then to ſo vile a ſubiect as the world? ſhall I be ſtaied from the noble ſeruice of my God, for the loue of any earthly vanities? No, no, all theſe I will trample vnder feete, and reckon of them no better then they are. And now my ſoule mount vp aloft vnto the place where all thy treaſure lieth: I will lift vp mine eyes to the hils from whence commeth all my help:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 120.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 17.37.</note> Eagle like will I ſoare aloft where my ſoules food is, and fixe my thoughts on none but Chriſt; he is the center from whence all my cogitations are drawne, and the circle to which they tend; let
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2273:38"/>the <hi>Marthaes</hi> of this world com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues about many things, ful well I know there is but <hi>vnum neceſſarium;
<note place="margin">Luke 10.41.42</note> one neceſſarie thing:</hi> God graunt mee with <hi>Mary</hi> to chuſe the better part. As for other pleaſures, I count them but bitter ſweetes, in regard of the ioyes of heauen, where is fulnes of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for euermore. As for other riches,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.18.</note> I count them all traſh, in reſpect of the glorious riches of the inheritance of Saints: all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honour I eſteeme as baſe, in reſpect of my glorious calling in Chriſt Ieſus: all other nobilitie I count obſcure, in reſpect of new birth and regeneration by the holy Ghoſt:
<note place="margin">Iohn 44.</note> all other beautie I eſteeme but foule,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.</note> in reſpect of the beautie of Bethel, which is made by Chriſt Ieſus without ſpot or wrinkle: all other buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings I deeme as ruines, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that building which is not made with hands,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.1.</note> but eternal
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2273:38"/>in the heauens:
<note place="margin">Matth. 10.37.</note> Father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter and brother, ſonne and daughter muſt needes giue place to the loue of Ieſus, or elſe I were not worthie of him my Sauiour. Let others reioyce in their wit and policie, my reioycing ſhall be the teſtimonie of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that in ſimplicitie and godly purenes, and not in fleſhlie wiſedome, but by the grace of God I haue had my conuerſation in the world:
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.12.</note> Let others be puft vp with knowledge of humane Arts and Sciences, yet I eſteeme no knowledge to the knowledge of Chriſt Ieſus and him crucified,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.2.</note> by which knowledge I may <hi>be able to comprehend with all Saints,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.18.19.</note> what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height, and to know the loue of Chriſt which paſſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</hi> Stoope downe all earthly happines to this, in regard wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of all other gaines are but loſſes, all other priuiledges are but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles;
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2273:39"/>
                     <hi>yea doubtleſſe I think all things but loſſe for the excellent knowledge ſake of Chriſt Ieſus my Lord,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.8.</note> for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue counted all things loſſe, and doe iudge them to be dung, that I may winne Chriſt, and might be found in him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>O ſweete Ieſu, how great and innumerable be the gaines which I finde in thee!
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> 
                     <hi>As the Hart brai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the riuers of water, ſo pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth my ſoule after thee,</hi> O Chriſt, my Lord, my God, my Sauiour and my Redeemer.
<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> 
                     <hi>Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue I in heauen but thee, and who is there on earth that I deſire in compariſon of thee?
<note place="margin">Cantic. 1.2.</note> Thy name is as an ointment powred out,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 9.6.</note> therefore the virgins loue thee.</hi> Thy <hi>name is Wonderfull, Counſellor, the mightie God, the euerlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.5.8.</note> Thou art <hi>that faithfull wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> that <hi>Prince of the Kings of the earth,</hi> that <hi>Alpha and Omega, the firſt and the laſt,</hi> which haſt <hi>the key of Dauid,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.7.</note> and openeſt and no
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2273:39"/>man ſhutteth,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.18.</note> and ſhuttest and no man openeth,</hi> yea the very <hi>keyes of hell and of death:
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> Ieſus Chriſt ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday and to day, the ſame for euer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O thou whom my ſoule loueth,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Chriſt the true gaine.</hi> Philip. 1.21.</note> my only gaine Chriſt Ieſus, thou art to mee both in life and death aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage.</hi> In life; for thus I liue, <hi>and yet not I, but Chriſt liueth in mee:
<note place="margin">In this life.</note> and in that I now liue in the fleſh, I liue by faith in the ſonne of God,
<note place="margin">Galat. 2.20,</note> who hath loued me, and giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for me.</hi> So that here what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Arithmetician can reckon vp my gaines euen in this life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by him?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Remiſſion of ſins.</hi> Epheſ. 1.7.</note> 
                     <hi>By him I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption through his blood, euen the forgiuenes of my ſinnes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his rich grace.
<note place="margin">Imputation of his obedience for our iuſtification.</note> He is made vnto vs of God wiſedome, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, ſanctification and redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and his full, perfect and alſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient obedience is made a gaine to me, ſillie, ſimple, vile, and ſinful creature by imputation. By him
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:2273:40"/>
                     <hi>we haue acceſſe through faith vnto his grace,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Acceſſe to God.</hi> Rom. 5.2.</note> wherein we ſtand, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce vnder the hope of the glorie of God:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Adoption.</hi> Rom. 8.15.</note> By him I am adopted to be the childe of God, yea heire of happineſſe and eternall bliſſe: By him I doe recouer backe againe that right and title to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Right vnto the creatures.</hi> Epheſ. 2.15.</note> which was loſt by <hi>Adam:</hi> By him the curſes of this life are turned into bleſſings;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Afflictions good.</hi> Rom. 8.26.</note> for all things worke together for the beſt to them that are in him. And what ſhall I ſay more? All that we haue wee haue in him, who is made all in all vnto vs; hee hath taken our pawne, and left vs his ſeale; he hath taken vpon himſelf our ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.16. Reuel. 1.6.</note> and inueſted vs with his merits; he hath made vs Kings and Prieſts vnto God, and euen in this life hath giuen vnto vs the earneſt of his ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Matth. 28.</note> with a full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance that hee will neuer faile vs.</p>
                  <p>But if in this life only wee had
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2273:40"/>hope in Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſt is ourgain in death.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.19.</note> we were of al men the moſt miſerable. Bleſſed be he the author of our bleſſedneſſe, who as he is our gaine in life, ſo is he alſo our gaine in death, in as much as he hath taken away the ſting of death, and hath changed the condition of it, by making it of the gate of hell, the priuie por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall of eternall life. <hi>O death,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.55.56.57.</note> where is thy ſting! O graue, where is thy victorie? the ſting of death is ſinne, and the ſtrength of ſinne is the law: but thankes be vnto God that hath giuen vs victorie through our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Yea after death in him doth reſt our chiefeſt gaine: for then ſhall we finde the vertue of his reſurrection, in raiſing vp our duſty bodies into fleſh again, which neuer ſhall corrupt; <hi>who ſhall change our vile bodie,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.21.</note> that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious bodie, according to the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie working, whereby hee is able to ſubdue all things to himſelfe.</hi> And
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2273:41"/>euen then when all other gaines ſhall proue mens loſſes, he to his will proue the onely gaine: <hi>For what ſhall it profit a man to win the whole world,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.26.</note> and loſe his own ſoule?</hi> or what ſhall hee loſe that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all the world to win Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>This is the treaſurie of infinite value;
<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> this is the fountaine from whence al goodnes floweth; this is the hand that ſtretcheth foorth all what we want vnto vs. Do we deſire riches?
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.18.</note> in him are all the treaſures, and his inheritance is glorious. Do we deſire pleaſures? <hi>At</hi> his <hi>right hand is fulnes of pleaſures for euermore.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> Do we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire honor? <hi>Behold what honor hee doth ſhew vnto vs, that we ſhould be called the ſonnes of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.1. Ioh. 1.16.</note> Doe wee deſire grace? <hi>Of his fulnes we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue grace for grace.</hi> Do we deſire peace?
<note place="margin">Iſai. 9.6.</note> he is <hi>the Prince of Peace,</hi> and bringeth that peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which paſſeth all vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Doe wee deſire know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:2273:41"/>
                     <hi>In him all the treaſures of wiſedome and knowledge are hid.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.3.</note> He is an eye vnto the blind, a leg vnto the lame, a hand vnto the weake, a gaine vnto the loſer, he is, and ſo wee ought to take him, all in all vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>A figge then for the imaginary treaſurie of the Popiſh Church,
<note place="margin">Againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts merit gaine.</note> wherein as in a cheſt, they ſay, are laid vp, not only the ouerplus of the merits of Chriſt, but alſo of Martyrs and Saints to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed in pardons at their vnho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers pleaſure. Is not Chriſt alone our full and perfect gaine? Is there not in him an alſufficient treaſurie for his Church? And are they not in him compleat? All o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaine is but matter for the dunghil: None for me but Chriſt. The woman in the Goſpell that had the bloodie iſſue deſired to touch the hemme of his garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.21.</note> I will preſſe in further not onely to touch him, but by a true faith
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:2273:42"/>as it were with both hands to lay hold and hang on him. <hi>Thomas</hi> deſired for his contentation, but to put his finger into his ſide;
<note place="margin">Iohn 20.25.</note> I will ſet before mine eyes Chriſt crucified, and diue both bodie and ſoule into his blood: <hi>Shew me,
<note place="margin">Cantic. 1.6.</note> O thou whom my ſoule loueth, where thou feedeſt, where thou lieſt at noone;
<note place="margin">Cantic. 2.4.</note> I will ſeeke him and take hold on him, and leaue him not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I haue gotten him:</hi> I care not to loſe all the world, to winne him, I eſteeme not the finding of any other thing, ſo I may be found in him.</p>
                  <p>There was a time when I was loſt,
<note place="margin">To be found in Chriſt.</note> he was the good ſhepheard which found mee the wandring ſheepe; there was a time when I was dead, yea dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, hee quickned mee to newnes of life; there was a time when I was a ſtranger, an alient from the common wealth of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.</note> he hath made me free of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:2273:42"/>celeſtiall incorporation, my de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſire onely is to bee found in him, that I may bee a member of that body wherof he is head,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15. Iohn 15.1. Iohn 6.56.</note> a branch of him the heauenly vine, that I may be in him and he in me, that by him I might be reconciled to God,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.14.15.</note> and accepted to his fauour eternally: <hi>Not hauing mine owne righteouſneſſe which is of the law,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.9.10.</note> but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, euen the righteouſneſſe which is of God through faith, that I may know him, and</hi> grow more and more in holy experience of the endleſſe loue of God, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable fellowſhip with Chriſt my Sauiour;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The vertue of his reſurrection.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.7. Rom. 8.34. Rom. 4.25.</note> that I may finde and feele in mee the vertue of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, whereby as I feele the full and perfect ſatisfaction of my ſinnes by him that died for my ſinnes, and roſe againe for my iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.1.</note> ſo likewiſe I may feele that ſpirituall viuification, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may bee raiſed vp from the
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:2273:43"/>death of ſin vnto newnes of life. That I may alſo know the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his afflictions,
<note place="margin">The fellowſhip of his afflictions.</note> and may learne to denie my ſelfe, and to take vp my croſſe daily;
<note place="margin">Luke 9 23.</note> and may bee made conformable vnto his death,
<note place="margin">Conformable to his death.</note> that as he died, ſo I may die to ſinne, and may feele within me the mortification of my fleſh,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.3. Epheſ. 5.3. Galat 5.34. <hi>Attaining to the reſurrection of the dead.</hi>
                     </note> by crucifying the affections and the luſt thereof, <hi>If by any meanes I might attaine to the reſurrection of the dead,</hi> that my ſleepie ſoule might awake from ſin, and ſtand vp from the dead, and might <hi>cast off concerning the conuerſation in times paſt the old man which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt through the deceiueable luſts,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14. Epheſ. 4.22.23.24.</note> and might be renued in the ſpirit of my minde, and put <hi>on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſnes and true holineſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ah alas,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.12.</note> I feele how rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious my fraile nature is, how ſhort I come of this marke to which all mine endeuours ought
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2273:43"/>to aime; vile wretch that I am,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> I am carnall, ſold vnder ſinne, and ſodden in iniquitie: <hi>For I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no good thing: to will is preſent with mee, but I finde no meanes to performe that which is good: for I do not the good thing which I would,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.19.</note> but the euill which I would not that doe I. O wretched man that I am,
<note place="margin">Verſe 24.</note> who ſhall deliuer me from this bodie of ſin?</hi> What way, what meanes ſhall I take to find my Chriſt and to bee found in him? This one thing will I doe,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.13.14.</note> I will <hi>forget that which is behinde, and endeuour my ſelfe to that which is before, and follow hard towards the marke, for the price of the high calling of God in Christ Ieſus: I will caſt away e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie thing that preſſeth downe,
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note> and the ſinne that hangeth on ſo fast, and runne with patience the race that is ſet before vs.</hi> I will ſing all worldly care away, and ſet my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections only in heauen.</p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:2273:44"/>
                  <p>Farewell my former vaine and tranſitorie delights; all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light now ſhall be vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints,
<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> and ſuch as excell in vertue: Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all other hope of gaine and thirſting after earthly pelfe; God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe I reckon ſtill to bee my greateſt gaine,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.6.</note> which hath the promiſes of this life and of the life to come:
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.8.</note> Farewell deſire of preferment and aduancement in this world; for I eſteeme the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke of Chriſt greater riches then all the treaſures of Aegypt:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.26.</note> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well all ouerweening loue of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,
<note place="margin">Matth 23.9.</note> wife, or childe, for there is one my father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, into whoſe hands I was caſt euen from my mothers wombe:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.11. Cant. 6.2.</note> 
                     <hi>I am my welbeloueds, &amp; my welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued is mine;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Sam. 1.8.</note> mine <hi>Elkanah</hi> is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto me then many ſonnes: Farewel affected knowledge and learnings lore;
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>for I eſteeme not to know any thing, ſaue Ieſus Chriſt and him crucified:</hi> Farewell hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2273:44"/>and artiſts ſtudies; my ſtudie ſhall be in the Librarie of the holie Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note> and therein will I meditate day and night: Fare well Philoſophie and diuing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Naturall cauſes; I will erect my thoughts vnto him that is the <hi>primum mobile,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 1.1.</note> the cauſe of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Farewell the knowledge of the Law and quirkes of earthly ſtatutes, the gleaning of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie is better then the whole vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> facultie: Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Phyſicke the lengthner of mens liues;
<note place="margin">Luke 5.31. Iohn 15.5.</note> my Phyſitian is the ſame that is my life: Farewell Geometrie and meaſuring of the earth;
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.20.</note> I will now meaſure the celeſtiall Globe of heauen in my thoughts: Farewell Aſtronomie, acquaintance with the Starres, ſoare vp I will aboue the ſtarrie skie,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.16.</note> to know him that in his right hand holdeth the ſeuen ſtarres: Farewell Arithmetique the Art of Numbring, <hi>Lord teach
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2273:45"/>me to number my daies,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.12.</note> that I may applie mine heart to wiſedome:</hi> Muſicke farewell; my muſicke ſhall be hencefoorth Halleluiahs to the King of Heauen:
<note place="margin">Reuel. 19.4.</note> Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well this world for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and welcome Chriſt Ieſus for euer.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:2273:45"/>
                  <p>THE WORLDS Wonder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS AND Worſhipfull Ladie, the Ladie <hi>Mary Ley.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame,
<note place="margin">Maſter Richard Greenham. Maſter Ioſeph Hall.</note> they which haue proceeded Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duats in the Art of Meditation, doe commend the infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite obiects in the Theater of the world, as the moſt fit ſubiect of Meditation. Reaſon ſheweth this their poſition to be moſt true: for where may wee haue either more
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2273:46"/>varietie of matter for our minds to worke vpon, or more readie meanes to ſet the ſame on worke, then in the great varietie of the worlds wonders, which are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually obuious to our eyes? The whole world is a table, wherein is portraited foorth vnto vs infinit wonders in the ſeuerall natures of all the creatures, not for vs to view alone, but with a fruitfull vſe to meditate vpon. All the creatures are made for Man, and ſhall not we be led by the proſpect of them to wonder at the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reſpect God hath to ſo poore a creature as Man? There is none of all the creatures but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs a lecture in this common ſchoole, and ſhall we be ſuch idle truants, as to learne nothing of ſo many maſters?</hi> The workes of the Lord are great,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 111.2.</note> and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2273:46"/>ought to bee ſought out of them that loue him:
<note place="margin">Verſ 4.</note> He hath made his wonderfull workes to be had in remembrance. <hi>O that wee vſing the creatures ſo continually as we do, would make better vſe of them then vſuallie we doe; I haue here ſet downe a little paterne of meditation in this kinde; had ſome skilfull</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles <hi>hand been in it, to draw and poliſh the lines of it, it might peraduenture bin worth the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſall. Now in this colour as it is, though I my ſelfe be ſilent in cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pardon for it, or excuſing it, yet you might iuſtly ſay vnto me as</hi> Apelles <hi>ſaid to an vnskilfull Painter,</hi> Though thou hadſt ſaid nothing, yet may I eaſily geſſe by the workmanſhippe that it was done in haſte. <hi>As it is, (Madam) I make bold to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2273:47"/>conſecrate this little Treatiſe to your name, the rather, for that (beſides all other reſpects of duty which doe oblige me vnto your Ladiſhip) you vouchſafed ſuch kinde acceptance vnto the firſt fruits of my labors in this kinde, which vnder your name was ſent to ſee the world: In hope of the like acceptation of theſe my poore endeuours, and fauourable par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of my boldneſſe, I commend this meditation following to your better meditations, and your ſelfe with all your holy medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Ladiſhips in all Chriſtian duties, G. W.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2273:47"/>
                  <head>THE WORLDS Wonders.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSAL. 8.9.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>O Lord our Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the world!</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Aul,</hi> the Apoſtle of the Gentiles, diſputing with the Athenians, the moſt wiſe &amp; learned amongſt the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">Act 17.22.23.24.27.</note> when hee ſaw their blind deuotions in ignorantly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing worſhip vnto <hi>God vnknowne</hi> (as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on one of their Altars he did perceiue) wondred much at this their ignorance,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> that this great God ſhould be to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnknowne, ſeeing that by <hi>groping after him</hi> they could not chuſe but finde him in the very workes of wonder which hee had done.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2273:48"/>For albeit <hi>the heauen is</hi> his <hi>throne,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.1. 1. King. 6.1.</note> and the earth</hi> his <hi>footſtoole, neither dwelleth</hi> hee <hi>in Temples made with hands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Act. 7.48. Deut. 4.15, 16.</note> and <hi>no man hath ſeene any ſimilitude or likenes of him at any time,
<note place="margin">Act. 14.17.</note> yet hath hee not left himſelfe without ſufficient witnes,</hi> not onely in his word, but alſo in his works; yea, <hi>The inuiſible things of him, that is,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> his eternall power and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head are ſeene by the creation of the world, being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered in his works, that men might be without excuſe.</hi> Which when I think vpon, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but wonder at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardlike Atheiſts ſoule-blinded monſters of our age,
<note place="margin">Againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts.</note> who <hi>in their hearts do ſay,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> There is no God,</hi> and whoſe vnderſtanding is ſo darke and dimme, that they cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne themſelues, nor ſee a God, that is the fountaine of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in ſo cleere a glaſſe as the mirrour of his creatures. They ſee an Heauen abundant in varietie of influences ouer them, an Earth
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2273:48"/>ſo plentifull in al ſorts of commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities vnder them, a Sea ſo full of wonders by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they ſee a world which is a building infinitly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, for the firmenes, capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, vſe, order, and motion of it, and in themſelues may ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a little world, or abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the greater world; and yet cannot ſurmiſe a God that was the compactor of this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and the endower of this Earth, and the controller of the Sea, the worlds both the greater and the leſſers Creator.
<note place="margin">Iſay. 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>O ye hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens</hi> be aſtonied <hi>at this,</hi> you bruit and ſenſeleſſe creatures conuince theſe reaſonable creatures vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and void of ſenſe.
<note place="margin">Iſay. 6.9. Rom. 11.8.</note> They are poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of ſlumber, and wilfully they winke with their eyes, like the Idols of the Heathen,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.15.16.17.</note> 
                     <hi>Eyes haue they but ſee not, eares but heare not, hearts but cannot vnderſtand.</hi> As for my part, I can no where fixe mine
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2273:49"/>eyes, but that I doe behold a liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Idoea of the incomprehenſible Deitie; the whole world being a booke or large volume,
<note place="margin">Du Bartus in oper. ſex dierum.</note> and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kinde of the ſo many kinds of creatures being a leafe or page, wherein in grand characters and great capitall letters are engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the wonders of our God moſt wonderful, ſo that he which runneth by cannot chuſe but reade it.</p>
                  <p>For firſt,
<note place="margin">The Heauens wonders.</note> when I look vp to the heauens, and fixe mine eyes on thoſe ſuperiour Orbes, me think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth theſe very <hi>heauens</hi> abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>declare the glorie of God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.3. Pſal. 19.1.</note> and the firmament ſheweth his handy work:</hi> whoſe huge proportion when I behold like molten glaſſe,
<note place="margin">Iob 37.18.</note> and meditate vpon the varietie of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences in the ſame, managed by ſo admirable a conſort of diuers motions which thwart, and yet diſturbe not one another, then ſaith my ſoule within it ſelfe; <hi>O
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2273:49"/>Lord my God,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.1.2.</note> thou art exceeding great, thou art clothed with glorie and honor,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.1.2.</note> which couereſt thy ſelfe with light as with a garment, and ſpreadeſt out the heauens like a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi> O how beautifull,
<note place="margin">Caelum beatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> how glorious, how admirable muſt the heauen of heauens be, ſeeing there is ſo glorious a luſtre in this lower heauen that is ſo obuious to our eyes!</p>
                  <p>Here he,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Sunne.</hi> 1. Iohn 1. Gen. 1.16.</note> who is all light him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, hath placed his two glorious lights, the greater for to rule the day, and the leſſer to be a nightly Torch: Here <hi>hath he ſet a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle for the Sun, which commeth foorth as a bridegroome out of his chamber,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.4.5.6.</note> and reioyceth like a giant to runne his race: His going out is from the end of the heauen, and his compaſſe is to the end of the ſame; nothing is bid from the heat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> It riſeth and goeth down,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.5.</note> and draweth to his riſing place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: who can expreſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2273:50"/>of this Planet,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plato in Epinar. Cicero.</hi> 2. <hi>de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Deorum.</hi>
                     </note> whoſe raies do illighten the whole globe of the earth, and therefore (though it ſeem but ſmal vnto our eyes, yet) reaſon demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrateth that it muſt needs ſurmount in greatnes al the earth?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> Who can deſcribe his cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his neuer wearied race?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Baſil. homil.</hi> 6. <hi>in Hexam.</hi>
                     </note> who can track his yeerely beaten path thorow the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack, or the milke-white way? what Eagle-ſighted eye dareth to confront his beames, and is not dazeled at his luſtre? what tongue is able to deſcribe his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, or paint foorth his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull effects?</p>
                  <p>Come we from this Landlord of light the Sunne vnto his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder,
<note place="margin">The Moone.</note> Heauens leſſer light, the Moone,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.16.</note> and who would thinke ſo full a bodie to our eyes ſhould be ſo many degrees inferiour to the Sunne in greatnes,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Plin. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> were it not for her neernes? who can record the influences of this palefaced
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2273:50"/>preſident of the night, or ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently admire her wainings, and encreaſings, her often changes and eclipſes? who can but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at her more then ſtrange ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the ſad and ſilent time of night,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.20.21</note> 
                     <hi>when the beaſts of the forreſt come abroad, and the hungrie lions rore after their pray?</hi> The more I fixe mine eyes vpon the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the more mine eyes are dazeled with the great varietie of wonders in the ſame:
<note place="margin">The Starres.</note> when I behold the glorious glittering canopie of Heauen ſo decked with ſtars,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.17.</note> as with ſiluer ſpangles or pretious ſtones, Lord thinke I then, how great a God art thou, <hi>which counteſt the number of theſe ſtarres,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.4.</note> and calleſt them all by their names?</hi> For, what man is able to diſcourſe, of their number, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, order, or ſituation? <hi>Can</hi> we <hi>reſtraine the ſweet influences of the Pleiades?
<note place="margin">Iob 38.31, 32, 33, 34.</note> or looſe the bands of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion? Can</hi> we <hi>bring foorth Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2273:51"/>in their times, or guide Arctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus with his ſonnes?</hi> No, no, it is the Almightie alone that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the courſe of heauen, and hee that <hi>in his right hand holdeth the ſeuen ſtarres,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.16.</note> that can ſufficiently declare the wonders of the ſtars.</p>
                  <p>He it is that ſheweth his <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the Heauen;
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Meteors fierie.</hi> Inel 2.30. <hi>The Bolides. Comets. Blaſing Starres.</hi>
                        </note> blood, fire and pillers of ſmoake,</hi> heart-dreading Comets, and doome preſaging blazing ſtarres are flagges of his imperiall ſtanderd; and who can but admire his diuers coloured Bow the enſigne of his couenant?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Rainbow.</hi> Gen. 9.16.</note> Behold our God is excellent and ful of power, neither can his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders be ſufficientlie admired at. <hi>The earth trembleth and quaketh when hee is angrie,
<note place="margin">The Lightning.</note> the foundations alſo of the mountaines ſhake at his diſpleaſure, a ſmoake goeth out at his noſtrils,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.7.8.9.14.</note> and a conſuming fire out of his mouth, coales are kindled thereat: He ſendeth foorth his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and ſcattereth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his fierce
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2273:51"/>lightnings flaſh from the one end of the heauen to the other.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Thunder.</hi> Iob 37.3.4.</note> After that a noiſe ſoundeth, hee thundreth with the voyce of his Maieſtie, and his Demicanons rore ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly through the clouds, that the vndantedſt <hi>Caligula</hi> cannot chuſe but quake and tremble at the noiſe thereof.
<note place="margin">Sueton. in vita Caligula.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Loe theſe are a part of the waies of God,
<note place="margin">Iob 26.14. <hi>Meteors atrie.</hi>
                        </note> but how little a portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue we heard of him,</hi> and who can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the one halfe of his workes of wonder?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The windes.</hi> Pſal. 104. Eccleſ. 1.6.</note> It is our God that <hi>bringeth the windes out of his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurie, and walketh vpon the wings thereof,</hi> euen the winde which goeth towards the South, and compaſſeth towards the North, and whirleth round about. The whirle winds and dreadfull blaſts are the wings vpon which hee doth flie:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The whirlewind.</hi> Pſal. 18.20. <hi>The Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes. Ariff. metcor. lib.</hi> 2. Pſal. 18.17. &amp; 19.6.</note> with the drie and cold vapors whereof paſſing thorow the cranies of the earth, <hi>he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the earth to tremble, and the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2273:52"/>foundations of the mountaines to ſhake, he maketh the wilderneſſe to tremble,</hi> and the Cedars of Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to be rooted vp.</p>
                  <p>Hearken vnto this,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Meteors watrie. The clouds.</hi> Iob 37.37.25.</note> O man, and conſider the wondrous works of God: <hi>Who can number the clouds by wiſedome?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 26.8.</note> who can ſufficiently admire theſe bottels of heauen? how the <hi>waters are bound vp</hi> in them, and the cloud not broken vnder them;
<note place="margin">The Dew.</note> how they are ſtuffed with watry vapors lift vp into the ayre,
<note place="margin">Iob 38.28.</note> and how the ſpouts thereof are diuided to powre down raine vpon the earth; how wonderfull is the generation of the drops of dew,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Mists.</hi> Pſal. 77.</note> which ariſeth out of the earth like a ſweat! or of the dew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropping Miſts, which like an hoarie mantell ouerſhadeth the earth! What a wonderfull thing it is to conſider the opening of the windowes of heauen,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Raine.</hi> Gen. 7.11. Iob 28.26. Pſal. 104.13.</note> and the diſtilling of the raine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, whereby the earth is watred, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2273:52"/>the thirſtie lands do quench their thirſt!
<note place="margin">The Snow.</note> How admirable is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnow which the Almightie ſcattereth abroad like wooll,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.13.</note> and which like a ſheete is ſpread vpon the earth!
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 47.18.</note> The eye maruelleth at the whitenes of it, it dazeleth the eye with the gliſtering ſhining of it,
<note place="margin">Et quae me ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit mater mox gignitur ex me.</note> the ſenſes ſtand aſtoniſhed to ſee it beget againe the mother of which it ſelfe was begotten. No leſſe wonderfull is the Haile which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Almightie caſteth forth like morſels,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Haile.</hi> Pſal. 147.17. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>properly ſignifieth haile in that place, though our tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations reade it frosts.</hi> Exod. 9.23.</note> a liquid thing being made ſolid, and it ſelfe being nought but water, yet by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiperiſtaſis of heate and cold (a thing in Nature admirable) is conglobated into a ſtone, deadly to the herbes, and noxious to the trees of the field. What ſhall I heere ſpeake of the Froſts,
<note place="margin">Meteors partly earthy, partly watrie.</note> or of the glaſſie wonder of the Ice; when the earth groweth into hardnes, and the clods like iron are faſt together?
<note place="margin">Frost.</note> The hoare froſts
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2273:53"/>lie vpon the earth like aſhes,
<note place="margin">Iob 38.29.38. Pſal. 147.16.17 <hi>Ice.</hi>
                     </note> who can abide the cold of the ice? When the North winde blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, an ice is frozen of the water, it abideth vpon the ſuperficies thereof,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Syracides, cap.</hi> 43 19.20.</note> and clotheth the waters as with a breaſtplate, the Sunne ariſeth and it melteth, and is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued as it was before. Theſe and many more then theſe are thy wonders, O Lord, from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: <hi>O Lord our God, how excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent is thy name</hi> in al theſe things! <hi>In wiſedome haſt thou made them all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.1.2.</note> and they declare thy mightie power. No leſſe are thy wonders to be ſeene here below, through the whole circumference of the earth and in the deepe.</p>
                  <p>For firſt to begin with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Earth it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">The Earths wonders.</note> which albeit in compariſon of the Heauen, it be but as a prick or point;
<note place="margin">Iob 38.18.</note> yet who can perceiue the breadth of it, or reckon the circuit of the ſame? The Earth is ſet vpon a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2273:53"/>immoueable,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ariſtot.</hi> 2. <hi>de coe lo, ait Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticos ſui temporit attribuiſſe terrae</hi> 40. <hi>myriades ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorum. Later Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers deſcribe the whole circuit of it to be</hi> 2000040 <hi>miles.</hi>
                     </note> and yet the foundation thereof is a thing of nought, hanging in the middle of the ayre: whoſe figure although it bee ſphaericall like a globe or bowle, yet by the alprouident diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Almighty Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, is ſo interlined with hils, and dales, and woods, and riuers; that in a wonderfull excellencie wee cannot but admire the infinite varietie.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.5. Iob 26.7.</note> Here wee ſee the loftie mountaines giuing ſtatelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect from their aſpiring tops; here,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mountaines.</hi> Pſal. 104.8. <hi>Vallies.</hi> Pſalme. <hi>Riuers.</hi>
                     </note> the humble Vallies to laugh and ſing with corne and graſſie profits; here, the cryſtall ſprings and ſiluer riuers ſliding, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times more ſilently, ſometimes in a baſſer ſort, ſometimes in a ſhril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler note making muſick amongſt the pepbles. And as we walke by the way, O what a glorious ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle it is to view the flagrant Meddowes cloathed with graſſe,
<note place="margin">Meddowes.</note> and enameled with al ſort of eye-pleaſing
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:2273:54"/>flowers;
<note place="margin">Woods.</note> Thickets lined with moſt pleaſant ſhade of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſorted Trees;
<note place="margin">Trees.</note> Trees richly decked foorth with leaues, and ſwelling in varietie with their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall kindes of fruites!
<note place="margin">Birds.</note> Oh what an heauenly conſort out of the Wood-quire reſounds vnto our eares from the cheerfull chirping of the many well tuned Birds! How ſweete a proſpect it is vnto our eyes to looke vpon the great varietie both in kind and qualitie of the Beaſts!
<note place="margin">Beasts.</note> To ſee the harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Sheepe feeding with ſober ſecuritie,
<note place="margin">Sheepe. Lambes.</note> and their pretie Lambs skipping with bleating choragy!
<note place="margin">Oxen.</note> To ſee the ſtrong necked Oxen laboring in the furrow and plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the vallies after vs; and the ſtately Horſe,
<note place="margin">Iob 39.12. <hi>Horſes.</hi>
                     </note> for all his fearefull neyings, to ſubmit his back vnto vs! when I fee theſe ſtrong and ſturdie beaſts ſo ouerruled, to yeeld their backs to ſeruing, and their liues to feeding weake and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:2273:54"/>feeble man, Lord thinke I then, of how vnmatchable power and vnbounded wiſedome art thou, which couldeſt ſubdue without repining theſe ſo great to this ſo little?</p>
                  <p>But when I further think vpon thoſe greater and wilder beaſts which God hath placed in the earth, in the maieſtie of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how can I but admire the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable maieſty of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Behemoh.</hi> Iob 40.10.11.12.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold Behemoh whom hee hath made to licke graſſe like the oxe, whoſe taile is like the Cedar,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 17.</note> his bones like ſtaues of braſſe, and his ſmall bones like ſtaues of iron; can the trees couer him with ſhadow, or can the willowes of the riuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe him about?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Lions.</note> The great and princely Lions roring after their pray, <hi>doe ſeeke their meate of God,
<note place="margin">Iob 39.1.2.</note> when they couch in their places, and remaine in the couert to lie in wait:</hi> He appointeth the time when the wilde goates bring foorth yong,
<note place="margin">Iob 39.4.5.</note>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:2273:55"/>and numbreth the moneths for the Hindes to calue:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 12.</note>Who can tame the Vnicorne and bring him to the crib? What pleaſant wings hath God giuen to the Peacocks?
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 16.</note>what wings of braſſe vnto the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrich? what length of daies vnto the Hart, ſwiftnes vnto the Hare, wilineſſe vnto the Fox, &amp; proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties admirable euen in euery ſort of the beaſts vnreaſonable? who can number their ſeuerall kindes, or deſcribe the ſeuerall natures of them?</p>
                  <p>But leaue wee theſe,
<note place="margin">Little beaſts and creeping things.</note> and caſt our eyes but on the leſſer crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which one would thinke but Natures excrements meere ſuperfluities: and yet, good Lord, in them how many workes of wonders? The wiſeſt of either Heathen or Chriſtian Sages ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs to little Piſmires,
<note place="margin">Emmets.</note> Ants or Emmets to learne diligence, <hi>for they hauing no guide,
<note place="margin">Prou. 6.6.7.8.</note> gouernour, nor ruler, prepare their meate in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2273:55"/>ſummer, and gather their foode in harneſt.</hi> What a ſweete decorum in their order obſerue the ſillie Bees,
<note place="margin">Bees.</note> the fabrick of whoſe celles or houſes, and the glory of whoſe merchandiſe cannot be matched by any wit or art of man? What Spinſter can make a webbe like the contemned Spider?
<note place="margin">Spider.</note> or Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer frame vpon his woofe ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite a forrell,
<note place="margin">Silkeworme.</note> as the little Silk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme weaueth out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels? If I ſhould reckon vp al the mightie wonders in theſe little creatures, how endleſſe would the ſubiect be? No, theſe are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and triuiall before our eyes, which euery where on earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wee ſee:
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.11. Pſal. 111.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Loe God hath made euery thing beautifull in his time;</hi> and where may we caſt our eyes but we may behold his works of wonder?</p>
                  <p>Should I meditate of all the fruitful ſeeds, and trees, and buds, from the Cedar vnto the Hyſſope
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2273:56"/>that groweth vpon the wall;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vertues of herbes.</hi> 1. King. 4.33.</note> O how ſecret &amp; hidden vertue may we behold in moſt of them? what eſpeciall vſe in each of them? Yea diue wee downe into the bowels of the earth, what ſtore of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects wonderful lie hidden there? There the Siluer mineral hath his veine,
<note place="margin">Iob 28.1.2.</note> and the burniſhed Gold his place; Iron is taken out of the duſt, and Braſſe is molten out of the ſtone;
<note place="margin">Verſ. 5.</note> out of the ſame earth commeth bread to ſtrengthen man,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.15.</note> 
                     <hi>and wine to make glad</hi> his <hi>heart, and oyle to make him a cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful countenance.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 6. Verſ. 17.</note> The ſtones there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are a place of Saphirs, Pearles, Rubies, Topazes, and pretious Iewels are taken out of her rocks. And ſhall I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tread vpon ſo rich a Theater as the earth, and not acknowledge the wondrous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God the founder? O, no, ſenſeleſſe and brutiſh creature were I then: Therefore this (my ſoule) muſt euer bee the burthen
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:2273:56"/>of my ſong, <hi>O Lord, how manifold are thy workes?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.24.25</note> In wiſedome hast thou made them all: The earth is full of thy riches, ſo is the ſea alſo great and wide, wherein are things creeping innumerable both ſmall and great.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which when I do behold,
<note place="margin">The Seas won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> and know that it is but water, (and that is an humor naturally ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) and yet ſee it higher then the earth,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.10.</note> againſt its owne nature without limit ſolid, <hi>Lord,</hi> thinke I then, <hi>how wonderfull are thy workes,</hi> thou mightie controller of the Sea? How could this be? How commeth this to paſſe? <hi>Surely thou haſt ſet vp the Sea with doores, and inuironed it with bars,
<note place="margin">Iob 38.8.10.11.</note> thou hast ſaid, hitherto ſhalt thou come, but no further, and here ſhalt thou ſtay thy proud waues. They that goe downe into the ſea in ſhips,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.23.24 25.26.27.28.29.</note> and occupy in the great waters, they ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe. For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2273:57"/>and raiſeth the ſtormie winde, and it lifteth vp the waues thereof: They mount vp to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and deſcend to the deepe, ſo that their ſoule melteth for trouble: They are toſſed to and fro, and ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger like a drunken man, then they crie vnto the Lord in their trouble, and hee bringeth them out of their diſtreſſe: He turneth the ſtorme to calme; ſo that the waues thereof are ſtill.</hi> In this liquid region goe the ſhips; there play the infinite multitude of fiſhes both ſmal and great;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.26.</note> there remaineth that <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiathan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The Whale.</hi> Iob 41.</note> whoſe <hi>skales are like ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſhields,</hi> whoſe <hi>bones are like barres of iron, his heart as ſtrong as a ſtone,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 6. Verſ. 15.</note> and as hard as the nether milstone, his neiſings make the light to ſhine, and his eyes are like the eye lids of the morning,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 9.10.11.</note> out of his mouth goe lamps and ſparkes of fire, his breath maketh coales to burne, he maketh the depth to boyle like a pot, and the Sea like a pot of oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:2273:57"/>Hee maketh a path to ſhine after him,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.23.24.</note> one would think the depth as an hoare head; in earth there is none like him:</hi> no, neither ſo great riches, nor ſo many wonders as in the ſea. How full of wonders then both heauen and earth and ſea! the eye of man beholdeth but a part of them, neither can mans heart conceiue the leaſt part of Gods mightie power in them. But for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were all theſe things made;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>All theſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for mans ſake.</hi> Gen. 17.1.</note> and why did God ordaine ſuch wonders in the wonders in the world? Surely not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, for he had no need of theſe things,
<note place="margin">Aſt. 17.28.</note> being himſelfe the alſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient eſſence, from whom all things haue their being. Neither were theſe things created onely for a ſhew, but for the vſe of man, whom God made in his owne image according to his own like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to rule <hi>ouer the fiſh of the Sea,
<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> and ouer the foule of the heauen, and ouer the beasts, &amp; ouer euery thing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2273:58"/>that creepeth and mooueth on the earth:</hi> which when I do conſider, <hi>Lord, ſay I then, what is man that thou art mindfull of him,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.5.6.</note> and the ſon of man that thou viſiteſt him? thou haſt made him heere on earth as a Demigod, &amp;c rowned him with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and worſhip. Thou hast made him to haue dominion in the worke of thine hands, thou haſt put all things vnder his feete;</hi> yea thou haſt made him the chiefeſt of all thy works of wonder.</p>
                  <p>For man being the laſt of all the workes created,
<note place="margin">The wonders in man. Sanctius his ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal mentiſque capacius altae d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erat ad huc.</note> and the end for whoſe ſake the reſt of the creatures were created, could not but be the chiefeſt and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect worke of all theſe worldlie creatures: and therefore is made by the eternal God as an epitome of the whole world;
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the perfect analogie and reſemblance betweene him and the great worlds frame, is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly tearmed the leſſer world;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2273:58"/>There being nothing in the vaſt compaſſe of the vniuerſal circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
<note place="margin">The reſemblance betweene man and the whole world.</note> whoſe likenes or liuely repreſentation is not ſummarily compriſed in man, as in a moſt perfect compendium or abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whoſe reaſon, as the moſt powerfull miſtris power of the ſoule, ſubdueth to her dominion and direction the ſeruill vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faculties and ſenſuall appetites, like as the firſt moued ſphere car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth with his motion the ſubiect inferiour circles;
<note place="margin">The Souie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth the Primum mobile.</note> whoſe heart ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the middle part of the body for his habitation, giueth life and heate vnto all the reſt of the parts of the bodie,
<note place="margin">The Heart.</note> whereby they bee preſerued &amp; inabled to performe their naturall and proper fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; like as the Sunne,
<note place="margin">The Sunne.</note> which being ſituated in the middeſt of Heauen, illighteneth all things with his raies, and cheriſheth the whole and all things therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with his life preſeruing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:2273:59"/>heate. The fabricke of whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die doth conſiſt of that neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently admired temperature of all the foure Elements, and no part of all his bodie but ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly compoſed, that euery part thereof may ſerue for a work of wonder. Who can ſufficiently expreſſe or wonder enough at the excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie of man, ſo little a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture made but of the duſt? That he by contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſoare vp to the skies, and be able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, aſpects, and effects of the celeſtiall orbe; that he ſhould ride vpon the Seas, and ſearch, and paſſe ouer the liquid floods; that he ſhould vendicate both earth and ſea vnto his profit, and domineere ouer the beaſts, and know the nature of all the creatures; that he ſhould contriue the Arts and Sciences to a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, and being abſent to ſpeak to men farre diſtant by letters written, that hee ſhould in this
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2273:59"/>mortalitie ſeeke after immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and haue a ſeate prepared for him in heauen, after life ended here on earth. <hi>O God, how wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are thy workes</hi> euen in our ſelues! No tongue is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe: though I did nothing elſe but wonder, I cannot ſufficiently admire it.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 116. Pſal. 92. Pſal. 111.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Surely this is the Lords doing, and it is maruellous in our eyes. O Lord how glorious are thy workes!
<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> An vnwiſe man doth not vnderſtand it, and a foole taketh no notice of it.</hi> But well I wot, the gracious God hath ſo made his maruellous workes, that they <hi>ought to be had in remembrance:</hi> O let me euer be meditating on them, and neuer be vnmindfull of the Creator of them, whiles I can not ſufficiently admire at them; let my ſoule in ſilence euer beate vpon this ſtraine:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.9.</note> 
                     <hi>O Lord our Lord, how excellent is thy name in all the world!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:60"/>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:2273:60"/>
                  <p>THE ANCHOR of the Soule: Or, THE ONLY SOLACE of a Chriſtian here in <hi>this life.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head>TO THE WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull Miſtris <hi>Gertrude Danteſie.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord (as</hi> Iob <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) doth viſit man euerie morning, and trie him euery moment.
<note place="margin">Iob 7.18.</note> Many and ſundrie are the waies of theſe his trials, Gods children haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of them, you your ſelfe
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2273:61"/>haue had your ſhare in them: I therefore ſend vnto you heere an anchor, wherewith at all times you may take ſure hold faſt, though the tempeſt ariſe, and the winaes blow,
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.26.</note> and the waues daſh neuer ſo violently againſt your ſhip. I commend this little medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation following vnto your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, not for the worthines of it, as it is here contriued, but for the ſweete comfort of that matter to which it aimeth. I know you are better ſtored with richer medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in your own breaſt, then my barren garden can preſent vnto you; yet I preſume ſo much vpon your wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted kindnes, that I doubt not of your acceptance of theſe my abortiue labours, who haue giuen me ſo great encouragement from time to time, by your attentiue preſence at my implumed Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2273:61"/>The Lord hath opened your heart (as he did the heart of</hi> Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia) <hi>to be atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiue to thoſe things which are taught;
<note place="margin">Act. 16.14.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of your ſexe and ranke, like</hi> Martha, <hi>encumber them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues about many needles things,
<note place="margin">Luke 10.41.42.</note> like</hi> Mary <hi>you haue</hi> choſen the better part. <hi>Goe on in that good courſe which you haue begun; if this poore mite which I offer here vnto you may in any ſort in this good courſe further you, I haue all that my wiſhes aime at. And ſo I commend the following me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation to your vſe and Gods bleſsing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours both in heart and endeuours, <hi>G. W.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:62"/>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:2273:62"/>
                  <head>THE ANCHOR of the Soule.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1. TIM. 1.15.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>This is a true ſaying, and by all meanes worthie to be receiued, that Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners; whereof I am chiefe.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Vguſtine</hi> (as <hi>Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius</hi> doeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord) for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more deepe impreſſion of his moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous meditation, was wont to chuſe out of <hi>Dauids</hi> heauenlie Pſalmes certain ſelect ſentences, which in his bed-chamber walles he cauſed to be engrauen, that he might reade and meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euen in his bed. Of all the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2273:63"/>ſentences in the booke of God, which I would chiefly chuſe to meditate vpon, this ſhall be my choiſeſt motto; of all the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant flowers in the garden of the Lord, this ſhall be the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſmelling poſie to my ſoule, whether I eate or drinke, or ſit, or walke, to muſe and meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this worthie word of Truth, by all meanes worthie to bee thought vpon, That no leſſe then the Sonne of God and Prince of peace Chriſt Ieſus my Lord my God, ſhould vouchſafe to come into the world, and take vpon him our nature, to ſaue ſinners his greateſt enemies, in which predicament, I, <hi>G.W.</hi> humbly and ingenuouſlie acknowledge my ſelfe to be the chiefeſt.</p>
                  <p>This is the anchor on which my billow-beaten Barke doth reſt, whiles it is ſailing through the Ocean of temptations to the cape of neuer failing Hope; this is my
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:2273:63"/>
                     <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> when my conſcience is called vnto her ſinnes account; this is my fortreſſe againſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies aſſault, my ſhield &amp; buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler againſt their fierie darts; the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of my faith, and full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of mine, yea mine owne ſaluation. Which although the Diuell bids my ſoule deſpaire of, and Antichriſt would faine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade me at the leaſt to make a doubt thereof, yet (bleſſed be the Lord my God) I feele the full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of his loue, neither needs my ſoule to wauer between hope and deſpaire. For why, we <hi>haue a moſt ſure word of the Prophets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and the Apoſtles, teſtifying the certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate thereof vnto our ſoules, whereto as to a ſtable pillar wee may leane.
<note place="margin">Luke 6.48.</note> The fabricke of my faith is not built vpon the ſand, whoſe foundation may ſhake or flit away: but it is built vpon the rocke, which all the windes and waues of Hell can neuer ſhake. If
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2273:64"/>Hope-well onely were the Cable of my ſhip, and I were forced to caſt Anchor at Aduenture, the Straits of care would be too deep for any hold, and waues of feare would quickly blow mee to the rocke Deſpaire.
<note place="margin">Liuius.</note> If like <hi>metius Suffetius</hi> his bodie, my ſoule were racked aſunder betweene hopes and feares, what comfort could I haue of any worldly comfort? or if my perſwaſion onely heerein were coniecturall grounded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on no better foundation then on likelihoods, how could I chuſe but be diſmaied with a mutinie of doubts? Or were my certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie herein but the warrant of a mortall man, I might be ſoone beguiled by truſting to ſo fickle ground. But this hope is more then hope, my confidence is not coniecturall but infallible, my warrant is ſealed vnto mee more then by the bare word of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man: For hee that hath the
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2273:64"/>words of truth, yea who himſelfe is Truth it ſelfe,
<note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> doth aſſure the truth of this vnto my ſoule.
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.21.</note> The Apoſtles which ſpake not of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but as they were inſpired from the holy Ghoſt, confirme the ſame vnto mee,
<note place="margin">Iohn 21.24. Epheſ. 4.30.</note> and I know their teſtimonie is true. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God whereby we are ſealed vp to the day of redemption,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.13.</note> hath ſealed the ſame vnto me, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the earneſt of it vnto my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.22.</note> Things that paſſe to and fro amongſt men,
<note place="margin">Perkins treatiſe of Conſcience.</note> though they bee in queſtion, yet when the ſeale is put to, they are made out of doubt; and the giuing of earneſt is an infallible ſigne and token vnto him that receiueth it, that the bargaine is ratified, and that he ſhall receiue the things agreed vpon. Why, goe to then; what needes thou doubt, my ſoule, or make any ſcruple of thy ſure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, ſeeing thou haſt it already vnder hand and ſeale, yea vnder
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2273:65"/>farre ſurer euidence then any wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, leaſe, ſeale, witnes, or any humane order can imagine? But more, my ſoule, God that hath ſealed it vnto thee, hath alreadie giuen thee the earneſt herein of his owne ſpirit, and therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto thy reſt, thou needeſt not feare, thou haſt a pledge al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie.</p>
                  <p>But yet,
<note place="margin">To acknowledge certaintie of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</note> me thinkes, I dare not be ſo bold; to be thus confident, fleſh and blood doubteth will come within the compaſſe of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, vnleſſe the ſame be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified by ſome ſpecial reuelation. <hi>Hagar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 2.</note> thou talkeſt like a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh woman; Is that preſumption which of purpoſe belongeth to thine apprehenſion and applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt. de verb. Dei, ſerm.</hi> 28.</note> To reſt on the full aſſurance of the forgiuenes of thy ſinnes, is not arrogancie, but faith; to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge what thou haſt recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, is not pride, but deuotion. Doeſt thou not heare, the Apoſtle
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2273:65"/>counſelling thee neuer to reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till thou haſt gotten the full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of this ſo great a benefit?
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.10. 2. Cor. 13.5.</note> Doeſt thou not heare thy bleſſed Sauiour perſwading thee aboue all other things to reioyce in this aſſurance?
<note place="margin">Luke 10.20.</note> And doeſt thou not heare him checking thee for this thy doubting; O thou of little faith, wherefore didſt thou doubt? Remember <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 4.20.22</note> how he did not doubt of the promiſe of God through vnbeliefe, but was ſtrengthned in faith,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.38.</note> being <hi>fullie aſſured:</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> that went not by hope well, but by knowing certainly; and <hi>Iames,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.6.</note> that willeth vs to be conſtant in faith, and not to wauer. Remember the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſe of God himſelf, who to as many as belieue in him hath giuen power to be the ſonnes of God, namely,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.12.</note> to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue in his name.</p>
                  <p>O but the multitude of my ſins ſtand vp as a rampier or mount
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2273:66"/>againſt me and biddeth me feare,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The multitude of our ſinnes may not debarre vs from the truth of this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance.</hi> Rom. 11.20.</note> and Satan telleth me that this full perſwaſion, is but only a fantaſie and ſtrong imagination of mine owne head, and that my nature being thus rebellious, I ſhould not ſtand ſo much on mine aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 42.11.</note> but feare. <hi>Why art thou ſo caſt downe, O my ſoule, and why art thou ſo diſquieted within mee?</hi> Cheere vp thy ſelfe: thou haſt <hi>not receiued the ſpirit of bondage to feare againe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.16.</note> but the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whereby thou crieſt, Abba, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and this ſpirit beareth witnes with thee that thou art the childe of God.</hi> For know (wrangling Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan) that I ſtand not vpon weake tearmes or blinde preſumptions,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aſſurance of ſaluation not eaſie to be had in all.</hi> Luke 12.32. Matth. 7.14.</note> like many a carnall Goſpeller, which notwithſtanding hee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that Chriſts flocke is ſmall, and that in compariſon few ſhall be ſaued, yet thinks this aſſurance of ſaluation to be an eaſie and a triuiall thing. No, no, I take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2273:66"/>of the full aſſurance of my ſaluation vpon a ſurer founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I flatter not my ſelf in mine owne conceit, but haue the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of a twofold witnes, the ſpirit of God beareth witneſſe with my ſpirit,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> that I am the child of God.</p>
                  <p>For loe,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tokens of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi> 1. Ioh. 4.13. Rom. 8.16.</note> what pregnant teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to this purpoſe finde I vnto my ſelfe. <hi>By this I know that I dwell in Chriſt, and hee in me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath giuen me of his ſpirit:</hi> which maketh me with boldnes to crie, <hi>Abba, father,</hi> vnto him, and this very ſpirit helpeth mine infirmities,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 26.</note> that whereas I know not to pray as I ought, the ſpirit it ſelfe maketh requeſt for mee with ſighes that cannot bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 7.10.</note> By this I know that my ſinnes are vndoubtedly pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<note place="margin">Galat. 5.17.</note> in regard that for ſinnes paſt I feele a godly ſorrow, for ſinnes preſent I finde a fighting and ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the minde againſt them,
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.18.</note>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:2273:67"/>for ſinnes to come I endeuour with religious care for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent them. By this I know vnto my ſelfe the aſſurance of life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
<note place="margin">Iohn 7.37.</note> becauſe I beleeue in him that is the author of life eternall; I hunger and thirſt after him, and ſo highly doe I value him, that all things elſe I eſteeme but dung in regard of him.
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.4.</note> By this I know the aſſurance of my ſinnes remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, becauſe my deſire is to keep his commandements;
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.3.</note> not as if poore I in any ſort could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme a perfect obedience vnto them, but becauſe in his accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the will of the beleeuer is taken for obedience. The loue to God and his children, is another teſtimonie of our tranſlation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life:
<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.14.19.21.</note> 
                     <hi>For hereby wee know that wee are of the truth, and ſhall before him aſſure our hearts: and if our hearts condemne vs not, then may we haue boldnes towards God.</hi> Away then, vile Satan, that faine
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2273:67"/>wouldeſt driue mee to deſpaire, and you maleuolent Sataniſts, that would haue me turne my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance into doubting: For this is a true ſaying, I haue the ſure te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the Prophets for it, and the double witnes Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and mine owne to ſeale it, I haue the pledge and earneſt of it alreadie, therefore I will reioyce in it.</p>
                  <p>O let this worthie ſentence be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in mine heart as in a book;
<note place="margin">And by all meanes worthie to be receiued.</note> let it bee grauen with an iron penne, and printed euer in my minde with the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond. For what ſweeter comfort can I finde?
<note place="margin">Iob 19.23.</note> what more ioyfull newes can I muſe vpon? What can be more acceptable then the welles of water to a thirſty ſoule? What more delightfull then in warre to heare of peace, in miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to heare of mercy, in the midſt of death to heare of life? and yet all this and more then this wee
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:2273:68"/>finde heere in this true ſaying, moſt worthie by all meanes to be receiued, that <hi>Chriſt Ieſus came into the world to ſaue ſinners.</hi> No newes like to this: no ſuch ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tidings euer was heard of in the world. Well might the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly newes carrier of the birth of this vnto the Bethlehemetiſh ſhepheards giue this <hi>encomium</hi> of it to their eares,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold I bring you tidings of great ioy that ſhall be to all people.</hi> Well might the Quire of Heauen chant foorth their Chriſtmas Carroll vpon the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it,
<note place="margin">Luk. 2.13.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Gloria in excelſis, Glorie be to God in the high heauens, peace in earth, and towards men good will.</hi> Well might old <hi>Simeon</hi> for a lul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labie vnto his Sauiour, ſing his <hi>Nunc dimittis,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.28.</note> Lord now letteſt thou, thy ſeruant depart in peace, for mine eyes haue ſeene thy ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> for there is no ſolace like to this, no ioy to be compared to it.</p>
                  <p>The more I thinke vpon it, the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:2273:68"/>more I doe admire it,
<note place="margin">That Chriſt Ieſus.</note> and ſtand amazed in the meditation of it; eſpecially when I call to minde the author and finiſher of this our comfort;
<note place="margin">Heb. 12.2.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Reuel. 1.</note> who being no leſſe then Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, and Prince of peace,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 9.6.</note> whoſe name is <hi>Wonderfull, Counſellor, the mightie God, and euerlaſting fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> whoſe being is from euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.8.</note> the <hi>Alpha</hi> and the <hi>Ome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga,</hi> the beginning &amp; the ending, which is, which was, and which is to come, euen the Almightie. Why: this rauiſheth my ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all admiration, that he, who was <hi>the heire of all things,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 1.2.3.</note> the <hi>brightnes of</hi> his fathers <hi>glorie, and engrauen character of his</hi> own <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Philip. 2.7.</note> ſhould make <hi>himſelfe of no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> and take <hi>vpon him the forme of a ſeruant,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Galat. 4.</note> to make vs that were children of the bondwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to be heires,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> 
                     <hi>euen the heires of God, and fellow heires with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;</hi> that hee, in whom was the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2273:69"/>fulnes of riches,
<note place="margin">Epheſ 2.7. 2. Cor. 8.9. Ioh. 6.35.</note> ſhould become poore, that hee might inrich vs; that hee, who was the bread of life, ſhould ſuffer hunger, to feed vs;
<note place="margin">Luke 4.2. Deut. 18.15.</note> that hee, who was the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of liuing waters, ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thirſt to ſatisfie vs; that hee, who was the light of the world,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 4.7. Ioh. 7.37.38. Iohn 8.12. Iohn 11.9. 1. Cor. 1.22.</note> ſhould liue obſcurely to illighten vs; that he, who was the power of God, ſhould be tempted, that he might ſtrengthen vs; that he, who was the life of the world,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.1. Iob. 1.4.</note> ſhould die, that he might quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs; that he, who himſelfe was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,
<note place="margin">Galat. 3.13.</note> ſhould ſuſtaine the curſe of the law, that he might deliuer vs,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.5.9.10.11.</note> and be wounded to heale vs, and bee broken for vs to ſtop vp our breach. Who can heere but acknowledge the infinitenes of his ſnſpeakeable loue? who can chuſe but ſay with <hi>Paul; O the deepnes of the riches both of the wiſedome and mercie of God,
<note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> how vnſearchable are his iudgements,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:2273:69"/>and his waies paſt finding out!</hi> Who can chuſe but ſay with <hi>Dauid; O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.4.</note> what is man that thou art ſo mindfull of him, or the ſonne of man that thou ſo regardeſt him!</hi> Who can but with the Church in the Canticles confeſſe that his name is <hi>a pretious ointment powred out,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cantic. 1.2.</note> becauſe of the ſweete ſauour whereof our hearts muſt needes bee allured to loue him and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire him?</p>
                  <p>Eſpecially if wee but meditate vpon that neuer ſufficiently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired loue of his,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Came into the world.</hi> Gen. 1.</note> who being the God of Nature, to free vs from the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our nature,
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.5.</note> took vpon himſelf our nature, &amp; came into the world to ſaue vs from the deſtruction of the world; me thinkes this one thing might bee ſufficient to woe and winne our loue to him, when wee conſider that he who had his ſeate aboue the Heauen of Heauens,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 148.4.</note> ſhould vouchſafe to come downe and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2273:70"/>dwell vpon the earth his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.1.</note> that he might draw vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him to heauen; that hee who was equall to the Father,
<note place="margin">Philip. 2.7.8.</note> ſhould humble himſelfe to bee a ſeruant, that he might purchaſe for vs the right of ſonnes; that hee which was God,
<note place="margin">Iohn 1.1.2.</note> ſhould not diſdaine to become that which wee are, that hee might make vs partaker of that place where he now is. The meditation of which in generall, though it bee enough to adde wings to the minde that is moſt dull, and worke an impreſſion in the ſoule that is moſt voide of ſenſe; yet if we take a further ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey in the particulars therof, and note the vnkinde entertainment of him ſo kind a gueſt, vnleſſe our heart were an heart of flint it can not chuſe but melt. For (ah alas) <hi>he was in the world,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.12.</note> and the world was made by him, and the world knew him not: he came vnto his owne, and his owne receiued him
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2273:70"/>not.</hi> The Bethlemits,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.7.</note> amongſt whom he was borne, would not affoord him houſeroome,
<note place="margin">Luke 4.29.</note> but ſuch as their oxen and aſſes were wont to lodge in: The Nazarites, his countrimen by education, driue him out of their citie to the top of an hill, to throw him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce downe headlong: And we, yea all of vs,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.</note> for whoſe ſakes he came into the world, what gaue wee him but the heauie burthen of our ſinnes for his welcome? His entrance into the world was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, his being heere dolorous, his departure he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ignominious. The place of his birth little Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leem,
<note place="margin">Mich. 5.2.</note> one of the leaſt of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands of Iudah;
<note place="margin">Matth. 2.6.</note> the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber where hee was borne, but a ſtable; the cradle in which hee was laid, but a manger; the ſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling bands wherein his ſacred bodie was wrapt,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.16.</note> but homelie ragges; the parties that firſt came to greete him, but ſillie ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2273:71"/>All things in the natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of him, ſo great a one, euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the loweſt degree of meanes. Thus grew <hi>he vp as a branch, and as a roote out of a drie ground,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.2.3.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neither forme nor beauty,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men did ſee him, that they ſhould deſire him. Deſpiſed was he and reiected of all men, a man full of ſorrowes, and one that had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of our infirmities: No ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was hee borne,
<note place="margin">Matth. 2.16.</note> but <hi>Herod</hi> fought to deſtroy him; no ſooner was he baptized,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.1.</note> but the Diuell ſet vpon him to tempt him; no ſooner was hee in his publique preaching,
<note place="margin">Matth. 15.40. Matth. 9.34. Luke 6.7.</note> but the Phariſies en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy him, the Sadduces accuſe him, the Scribes ſlander him, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people ſcorne him,
<note place="margin">Matth. 13.55.</note> the high Prieſts ſend their officers to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap him,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.45.</note> his owne Diſciple ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to betray him,
<note place="margin">Marth. 26.48. Matth. 26.60.</note> falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes are ſuborned to belie him, and toſt he is from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 23.7.8.</note> and from <hi>Herod</hi> back againe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:2273:71"/>to <hi>Pilate,</hi> to mock him and make ſport of him:
<note place="margin">Matth. 27.28.32.35.</note> neither did they leaue vntill that after much buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, torturing and tormenting, by a cruell death they had made away with him. So cold an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment found he in this world, to ſhew that his kingdome was not of this world: He had no le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of men or angels to bee his guard, no chariots nor horſemen to be his pompe, no palace to bee his court: He wore no crowne but that of thornes, no Scepter but that of Reed, no throne but that of his croſſe: In his life time not hauing ſo much as a foxes hole to couch in; at his death not hauing a ſhroud, but what was left him, to bee wrapt in; nor a tombe, but what was borrowed, to be buried in.</p>
                  <p>What ſhall I here recount his grieuous paines and direfull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, which, while he was in the world, hee ſuſtained heere? My
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:2273:72"/>ſoule guſh out with teares of blood, whiles thou doeſt call to minde the ſorrow of his ſoule, when in Gethſemane his ſoule was <hi>heauie euen to the death,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 26.36.37 38.</note> when though an Angell from heauen appeared to comfort him, yet his agonie was ſo bitter, that his ſweate was like drops of blood trickling downe to the ground:
<note place="margin">Luk. 22.43.44.</note> O let mine head be full of water, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.1.</note> that I may weepe day and night for the afflictions which he endured who was afflicted for my ſinnes:
<note place="margin">Matth. 26.49.</note> when I call to mind thoſe diſmall daies, wherein my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours owne ſeruant did betray him with a kiſſe,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 55.</note>and the High Prieſts catchpoles came foorth with clubs and ſtaues and ſwords to apprehend him like a theefe;
<note place="margin">Iohn 18.12.</note> when hee that made vs free was bound, and haled, and dragd, and brought as a ſheep to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.7.</note> as a lambe dumbe before his
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2273:72"/>ſhearer, ſo hee opened not his mouth. Bitter be the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of that gloomie night,
<note place="margin">Iob 39.</note> and let the ſtarres of the twilight be dimme through the darknes of it, when he that gaue others often ſight,
<note place="margin">Mark. 8.22. Mark. 10.46. Iſai. 9.1.</note> and came to lighten thoſe that ſate in darkneſſe, himſelfe was blindfolded to bee made a ſcorne of; he that neuer offered wrong,
<note place="margin">Matth. 4.15.</note> and when himſelf was wronged, opened not his mouth,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.64.</note> was buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſmitten on the cheeke; that face,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.7.</note> that glorious face of his which on mount Thabor ſhined as the Sunne, was made a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Iewiſh ſpitting place,
<note place="margin">Matth. 17.2. Mark. 14.65. Pſal. 45.6. 1. Cor. 4.9. Iob 3.6.</note> and himſelfe, the head of men and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, made a gazing ſtock to men and angels. Let that day be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and not bee ioyned to the daies of the yeere, nor come into the accounts of the moneths, wherein with ſighes and ſobs I call not to minde that dolefull day; when hee which one day
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:2273:73"/>ſhall come in the clouds with glorie and great maieſtie,
<note place="margin">Matth. 24.30.</note> was brought before the tribunall of an earth pettie Iudge,
<note place="margin">Matth. 27.1.</note> and ſtood at the barre with all diſgrace and infamie;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 53.7.</note> when hee the innocent Lambe was arraigned, &amp; though found not guiltie was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wrongfully;
<note place="margin">Matth. 27.22.</note> hee the prince of glory was placed as a grieuous malefactor between two thieues,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 19.18.</note> his ſacred hands and feete being nailed to the croſſe;
<note place="margin">Iohn 19.2.</note> his head ſcratched rent and torne with a thornie crowne, and his ſacred ſides pierced thorow with a gaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſouldiers ſpeare,
<note place="margin">Iohn 19.34.</note> with which there guſhed foorth both blood and water. Behold &amp; ſee if there were any ſorrow like vnto this ſorrow which is done heere vnto my Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Lament. 1.12.</note> wherewith the Lord afflicted him in the day of his fierce wrath: witnes the grieſtly, gaſtly grone giuen by himſelfe whiles hee was hanging on the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:2273:73"/>croſſe, when that hee bellowed foorth his <hi>Eli, Eli,
<note place="margin">Matth. 27.46.</note> lamaſabachtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni; My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> Witnes the whole face of Nature chaunged at his ſuffering,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 51.</note>The Sunne being clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in blacke,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 52.</note>the pillers of the earth rocking,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 53.</note>the vaile of the temple renting, the rocks ſhieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and the very graues them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues opening their more then braſen gates.</p>
                  <p>But why was al this?
<note place="margin">To ſaue.</note> and what was the end of Chriſt his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the world, and his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of ſo many things heere in the world? Surely he came for vs, not for himſelfe, he came to ſaue. Therefore did the Lord anoint him, therefore did hee ſend him, that he might <hi>preach good tidings to the poore,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 61.1.</note> and binde vp the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hearted, and preach libertie to the captiues, and to them that are bound the opening of the priſon: To preach the acceptable yeere of the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:2273:74"/>Lord,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 2.</note>to comfort them that mourne, to giue beautie for aſhes, the oile of ioy for mourning, the garment of gladnes for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, that they might bee called trees of righteouſneſſe,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 8.</note>the planting of the Lord, that hee might be glorified.</hi> This was the good ſhepheard that came to ſeek vs loſt and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring ſheepe;
<note place="margin">Iohn 10.</note> this is that mighty champion which came to deliuer vs from the iawes of the lion and the wolfe;
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.34.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Numb. 21.9.</note> this is that brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent which cureth vs ſtung to the heart by that old fierie Serpent Satan;
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.14.</note> this is that good Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, whoſe comming was to heale our ſores:
<note place="margin">Luke 10.33.</note> The good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian who came to ſaue vs from death.
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.12. Iohn 10.10.</note> He came to ſaue: ſo ſaith he himſelfe, <hi>I am come that they might haue life, and haue it in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance.</hi> So ſaith the Angell of him which brought newes of his comming into the world, <hi>Vnto you this day is borne a Sauiour,
<note place="margin">Luke 2.11.</note>
                        <pb n="137" facs="tcp:2273:74"/>which is Chriſt the Lord.</hi> O ſweete Ieſu,
<note place="margin">Cantic. 1.2.</note> thy very name is as an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment powred out to make the virgins loue thee. Well maiſt thou be called Ieſus, for there is no other name vnder heauen whereby we may be ſaued,
<note place="margin">Matth. 2.27.</note> but by thine, whoſe name agreeth with thy nature, to ſaue the people from their ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>The very ſauour of which ſo flagrant ointment of his pretious name,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sinners.</hi> Cantic. 1.2.3.</note> as it well may draw the loue of all good hearts vnto him, and make them runne after him: ſo when I further conſider with my ſelfe our qualitie and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what we were when firſt he caſt his loue vpon vs, me thinkes it carrieth mee beyond admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that ſo great a Sauiour ſhould ſo much as reſpect ſuch vile and miſerable wretches: for this ſo ſweete a Sauiour came not to call the righteous,
<note place="margin">Matth. 9.13.</note> but ſinners to repentance. Were we righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:2273:75"/>No, there was none righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<note place="margin">Pſal 14.2.3.</note> no not one: we were all gone out of the way, there is was none of vs all that did deſerue his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, no not one. Were wee his friends that hee did impart ſuch kindnes vnto vs? Nay, wee were his deadly enemies, we were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.9.</note> Doubtleſſe one would ſcarſe die for a righteous man: but God ſetteth out his loue towards vs, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiles we were yet ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners Chriſt died for vs. The partie offended came to helpe the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the iuſt to die for the vniuſt, the innocent for the guiltie, the king of peace for his enemies, Chriſt Ieſus to ſaue ſinners. We were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wherein wee walked accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the courſe of the world, and after the prince that ruleth in the aire;
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.3.4.</note> but he rich in mercie through his great loue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he loued vs, was content to die for vs to quicken vs. We were
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2273:75"/>
                     <hi>alients from the common wealth of Iſrael ſtrangers from the couenant,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.12.14.19.</note> without hope, without God in the world: He is become our peace, who by breaking downe the ſtop of the partition wall, had made vs of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and forrenners, citizens with the Saints and of the houſehold of God:</hi> Our habitation &amp; our kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred was of the land of Canaan,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 16. Verſ. 3.</note> our <hi>father</hi> was <hi>an Amorite, and</hi> our <hi>mother an Hittite:</hi> in our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie when we were borne,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 4.</note>our nauell was not cut, wee were not waſhed in water to ſoften vs,
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 5.</note>nor ſalted with ſalt, nor ſwadled in clouts:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 6.</note>None eye pitied vs to doe any of theſe things vnto vs, or to haue compaſſion on vs: then did he paſſe by vs, &amp; ſaw vs polluted in our own blood, he ſaid vnto vs euen then when wee were in our blood, Thou ſhalt liue:
<note place="margin" type="runSum">Verſ. 8.</note>He ſpred his skirts ouer vs and couered our filthines, and made a league and couenant with vs: when we were
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:2273:76"/>ſinners he came to ſaue vs,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.7.</note> when we were his enemies hee came to ſeeke vs, when we were yet of no ſtrength he died for vs.</p>
                  <p>Wherein as we cannot but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the riches of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable loue, who loued vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee were, and followed vs with his loue, when we were his enemies; ſo may it well aſſure vs of his perpetuall loue and fauour towards vs.
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.8.9.10.</note> For, <hi>ſeeing that whiles wee were yet ſinners Chriſt died for vs, much more then being now iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by his blood ſhall we be ſaued from wrath through him: If when we were enemies we were reconciled to God by the death of his ſonne, much more being reconciled</hi> wee <hi>ſhall be ſaued by him.</hi> What then though the bedroule of our ſins reach vp to the clouds, and vice attracting vapors doe ouerſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow my ſoule as innumerable as Atomes? what though our rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious nature will not be kept in as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:2273:76"/>we deſire, and Satan pleade full ſore to bring our hearts to deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, heere, heere our endleſſe comfort is,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.18.</note> be our <hi>ſinnes as crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, they ſhall be made as white as ſnow, though they bee of a skarlet</hi> engrained <hi>die, they ſhall be made as white as wooll.</hi> For this is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor on which aſſuredly we may repoſe our truſt, <hi>This is a true ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and worthie by all meanes to be receiued, that Chriſt Ieſus came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to ſaue ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if in generall only this my comfort were,
<note place="margin">Whereof I am chiefe.</note> that there was a Ieſus Chriſt, that hee came into the world, and that his comming was to ſaue, and yet not feele the aſſurance of my part and portion in it; cold comfort, God wot, would this be to my ſoule, ſmall matter for me to reioyce. Nay, bleſſed be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> author of my peace, I can apply it to my ſelf:
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12.</note> for I haue boldnes and confidence by faith in him to put my finger into his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:2273:77"/>ſide with <hi>Thomas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.28.</note> and to ſay, <hi>My God, my Lord,</hi> to call him my Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, my Chriſt; and to relie whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by faith vpon this Son of God, <hi>who hath loued</hi> me,
<note place="margin">Galat. 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>and giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> for me; yea euen for me, <hi>G.W.</hi> the meaneſt, pooreſt, vileſt, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt of all Gods children, the greateſt and moſt miſerable ſinner in the world:
<note place="margin">Rom. 7.18.</note> 
                     <hi>For I know that in me,</hi> in this my ſinfull wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched fleſh, <hi>dwelleth no good thing;</hi> from the ſole of my foot vnto my head,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.6.</note> there is nothing whole but wounds, and ſwellings and ſores full of corruption. In ſinne was I conceiued,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note> in ſin was I borne, ſin ſeaſed vpon my childhood, and hath lackied my life vnto this my youthfull age, and the longer I liue, the ſurer foothold getteth foule ſin in my boſome, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the contagion in my ſoule: How huge a maſſe of ſinne lieth in me, hidden from mine eyes, which take poſſeſſion on me, and
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:2273:77"/>I, poore I, neuer tooke notice of them? Theſe, O theſe that I ſee before mine eyes, by looking in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bottomleſſe gulfe of my ſins, appeare as many as the ſtars in the skie, or drops of water in the Ocean ſea. When I looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelfe, I am aſhamed of my ſelfe; me thinkes the heauens o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me caſt a dire aſpect vpon me, and the albearing earth groneth vnder the ſinfull burthen of me; me thinkes the Sunne is aſhamed of me, and the palefaced Moone lookes wanne vpon me, and the airie clouds doe mourne for me. I cannot chuſe but wonder how in ſo little a ſubſtance, as my ſoule, ſhould be ſo great a ſinke of ſin. Of this ſure I am, I know none ſo ſinfull as my ſelfe, neither haue I any reaſon to imagine how any can be a greater ſinner then my ſelfe; yet why ſhould I deſpaire? <hi>I know that my Redeemer liueth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 19.25.</note> and hee liueth to bee my Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:2273:78"/>Though my ſins were more, hee could pardon them: though they were a thouſand times grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then they be, he hath ſatisfied for them. Be they black &amp; vgly? his blood hath waſhed them: Be they great and many? hee hath paid the ranſome for them: Be they heauie &amp; waightie? he hath mercie in ſtore for them. Heere then will I caſt my anchor, and pull downe the ſailes of feare, to harbour in this ſafeſt hauen: let the fleſh ſay, deſpaire, and the world ſay, relent, and the Diuell ſeek to cut the cable of my hope; yet my footing is ſure, I know on whom I fixe my hope, euen on Chriſt Ieſus, yeſterday, and to day, the ſame for euermore.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:2273:78"/>
                  <p>THE MOVRNERS Lamentation: Or, THE BEWAILING OF the miſeries of our times, with <hi>Gods fearefull iudgements to be expected for the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head>TO THE WORSHIP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my Chriſtian neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and moſt religious hearer, Miſtris <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie Long.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would ſhew to the Prophet</hi> Ezechiel <hi>the deſtruction of the Citie Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:2273:79"/>he is brought in by the ſame Prophet ſpeaking thus vnto one of his Agents herein;</hi> Goe through the midſt of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 9.4.</note> euen through the midſt of Ieruſalem, and ſet a marke vpon the foreheads of them that mourne, and crie for all the abominations that bee done in the middeſt thereof. <hi>Doubtleſſe many ſuch mourners are there in our Ieruſalem, whoſe teares are put in Gods bottle, and for whoſe ſake the Lord yet ſpares this our Iſrael: the Lord encreaſe the number of them. For (God knoweth) we had need call one an other to mourning, and take vp continuall lamentation: for who ſeeth not how rotten ripe the ſins of this land are,
<note place="margin">Amos 5.16.</note> and how deep all eſtates of the ſame are ſetled vpon the lees of their tranſgreſsions?
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:2273:79"/>And who can chuſe but feare that there is a day of wrath,
<note place="margin">Zephan. 1.15.</note> of trouble and heauines, of woe and horror neere approching? For mine own part, what deepe impreſsion the meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof maketh in mine heart, he knoweth which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſecrets of all mens hearts. One of my priuat contemplations which I haue communed with my owne heart in ſilence,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note> I heere make publique, by communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to you and others: To you eſpecially, becauſe I know you to be one of the mourners in Sion, as hauing had experience of your zeale to Gods houſe, loue to his word, and hatred to the common corruptions euer ſince you came to be partaker of the vnworthie labours of my miniſtry. The Lord encreaſe that good worke which long ſince he hath begun in you.
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:2273:80"/>This little Enchiridion, if you pleaſe, you may binde vp in the volume of your daily meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Thus to mourne, is neither hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to our ſelues, nor offenſiue to our Church. We may be merrie in the Lord, and yet without light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; ſad and heauie in heart for our own ſins and the corruptions of our times, &amp; yet without dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhnes. If we</hi> forget Ieruſalem, let <hi>our</hi> right hand forget to <hi>play;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.5.6.</note> if <hi>we</hi> remember not the peace of <hi>this our</hi> Sion, let <hi>our</hi> tongue cleaue to the roofe of <hi>our</hi> mouth, yea if <hi>wee</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre not Ieruſalem to all <hi>our</hi> mirth.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours intirely in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>G. W.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:2273:80"/>
                  <head>The Mourners <hi>Lamentation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>PSAL. 119.126.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>It is time for thee, O Lord, to work for they haue deſtroyed thy law.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Rue it is, Lord, that we are not to appoint thee thy times and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, for thou art the <hi>Ancient of daies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Daniel 7.9. Gen. 1.15.</note> Times Creator and deſtinator. Neither doe wee preſume to preſſe in at the portall of thy priuie chamber, to <hi>know the times and ſeaſons</hi> which thou our Father haſt <hi>reſerued</hi> in thine <hi>owne power:</hi> yet, Lord,
<note place="margin">Act. 1.17.</note> thou haſt taught vs, as to diſcerne the face of the skie,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.3.</note> ſo to deſcrie the ſignes of times, and from the cauſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the effect which neceſſarily
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:2273:81"/>doth enſue.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou art a God full of compaſſion and mercie, ſlow to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and of great kindnes,</hi> and thou doeſt ſuſtaine many wrongs of the ſonnes of men, being cruſhed with their ſinnes, <hi>as a cart is laden with ſheaues:</hi> but if ſtill they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to load thee, thou wilt eaſe thy ſelfe of that burthen, and caſt it on the ground of confuſion. Thou art <hi>ſlow to anger,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nahum 1.3.</note> but <hi>great in power, and wilt not ſurely cleere the wicked.</hi> Thou doeſt for a long ſpace hold thy peace at mens ſins and art ſtill,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 42.14. Pſal. 7.12.</note> and doeſt reſtraine thy ſelf: <hi>but if</hi> men <hi>will not turne,</hi> thou <hi>wilt whet</hi> thy <hi>ſword, and bend</hi> thy <hi>bow,</hi> and <hi>make it readie.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient thou art, and for a long time doeſt forbeare thine hand: but when the forehead of ſin begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to loſe the bluſh of ſhame, when the beadrole of tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions do grow in skore from Eaſt to Weſt, when the crie of them pierceth aboue the clouds, when
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:2273:81"/>the height of wickednes is come vnto the top,
<note place="margin">Gen. 15.16.</note> and the fruits there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are ripe and full, then it is time for thee Lord to take notice of it, to awake like a giant,
<note place="margin">Gen. 18.21.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> and to put to thine alreuenging hand.</p>
                  <p>But our ſins are alreadie ripe, yea rotten ripe, the meaſure of our iniquities is full vp to the brimme. Doubtleſſe our land is ſunken deepe in iniquitie;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.8.</note> Our <hi>tongues and works haue bin againſt the Lord to prouoke the eyes of his glorie;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.9.</note> the triall of</hi> our <hi>countenance doth teſtifie againſt</hi> vs, <hi>yea</hi> wee <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> our <hi>ſinnes as Sodome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 18.20.</note> we <hi>hide them not,</hi> the crie of our ſinne is exceeding grieuous,
<note place="margin">Iam. 5.4.</note> the clamors of them pierce the skies, and with a loud voice rore, ſaying: <hi>How long Lord, holy and true?
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.10. Ierem. 9.9.</note> how long ere thou come to auenge thy ſelfe on ſuch a nation as this is?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If there were but one vniuſt man amongſt vs,
<note place="margin">Sinne in all ſorts of people.</note> iniquitie for this one mans ſinne were lamentable;
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 7.1.</note>
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:2273:82"/>much more now when whole families, nay whole ſtreetes, yea whole towns and cities are ſuch, the caſe is to bee lamented, and the eſtate to be feared; when like a Gangrene ſinne hath eaten tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row euery ranke of people, and in a bodie politique <hi>from the ſole of the foote vnto the head there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whole therein,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.6.</note> but wounds and ſwellings, and ſores full of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Children.</hi> Pſal. 22.31.</note> when our yong children which ſhould be a ſanctified ſeed to ſerue the Lord, ſucke blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie from the dugge, and not learne to ſpeak before they learne to ſweare, filling each houſe, and ſtreete, and high way with their othes:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In yong men.</hi> Eccleſ. 12.1.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our yong men which ſhould remember the Lord in the daies of their youth, haue their heads full of drunkennes, their eyes full of adulterie, their tungs full of ribaldrie, their eares full of flatterie, their hands ful of blood, their feete full of vanitie, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:2273:82"/>only and calamitie being in their waies,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.3.</note> and no feare of God before their eyes. When our old men which ſhould be ſober,
<note place="margin">In old men.</note> are giuen to drunkenneſſe; which ſhould be chaſt,
<note place="margin">Tit. 2.2.</note> are giuen to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonnes; which ſhould be diſcreet, are full of fooliſhneſſe; which ſhould be ſound in the faith, are as ignorant as horſe and mule; which ſhould be in charitie, are full of enuie; which ſhould take their farewell of the earth, are the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt greedie of the earth, when themſelues are more then halfe earth.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In women.</hi> 1. Tim. 2.9.</note> When our women which ſhould adorne themſelues with ſhamefaſtnes and modeſtie, ſtriue who can moſt diſguiſe themſelues in cloathes of vanitie,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.16.</note> and in ſtead of hauing the hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man of their heart vncorrupt,
<note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> looke onely to their outſide to paint that vnto the world.
<note place="margin">In the Commons.</note> When our common and ordinarie ſort of people are <hi>murmurers, complainers,
<note place="margin">Iude 16.17.</note> walkers
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:2273:83"/>after their owne luſts, makers of ſects, fleſhly minded,</hi> and ful of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanenes. When the children ſhall <hi>preſume againſt the ancient,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.5.</note> and the vile againſt the honorable.</hi> When young and old ſhall thus openly, without bluſh of ſhame, expoſe their ſins to the ſunſhine of the world, when euery one hunteth his brother with a net,
<note place="margin">Mich. 7.8. Pſal. 12.2.</note> and in one body there is a double heart:
<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Shalt not thou be auenged for theſe things, O Lord? ſhall not thy ſoule be auenged on ſuch a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as this?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But bee it that generally the common ſort of men were ſo ill inclined;
<note place="margin">In Miniſters.</note> yet ſo long as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Lords vineyard were vnpolluted with blood,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Groenham in his common place of ſinne, cap.</hi> 62.</note> there were ſome hope the reſt might bee recouered: But when they which ſhould be eyes to others, themſelues are blinde as beetles;
<note place="margin">Matth. 6.23.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they which ſhould be lamps to others,
<note place="margin">Matth. 5.14.</note> haue no oyle within
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:2273:83"/>their lamps; when they which ſhould bee Paſtors to feede the flock of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.8. Ezech. 34.2.3.</note> clothe themſelues with the fleece, and eate of the fat, but feed not the ſheep;
<note place="margin">Malach. 1.7.</note> when they at whoſe mouth the people ſhould ſeeke the knowledge of the law, ſpeake <hi>good of euill,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.20.</note> and euill of good, put darknes for light, and light for darkneſſe, bitter for ſweete, and ſweete for ſower:</hi> when they that ſhould be faithfull ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.42.</note> giuing to Gods houſehold their portion of meate in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.17.</note> make merchandiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God, ſelling the cauſe of the Lord for handfuls of barley and pieces of bread:
<note place="margin">Ezeth. 13.19.</note> when they which ſhould <hi>ſhew the people their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.1.</note> and the houſe of Iacob their ſinnes,</hi> heale <hi>the hurt of the people with ſweete words, ſaying, Beace, peace, when there is no peace;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. 6.13.</note> when they that liue of the Altar,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.13.</note> liue from the Altar, and working euill in the eyes of the people,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:2273:84"/>cauſe men through their propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to abhorre the offering of the Lord:
<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.17.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.126.</note> Is it not then high time for God to put to his hand, and to viſit our coaſts?</p>
                  <p>Yet all hope of remedie were not altogether cut off,
<note place="margin">In Magiſtrates.</note> if they which are in authoritie would put to their reforming hands in this extremitie. But when ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall lull aſleepe authoritie;
<note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> when they that beare the ſword are afraide to ſtrike; they that ſhould plead Gods cauſe,
<note place="margin">1. King. 18.21.</note> halt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and <hi>Baal;</hi> they that ſhould be zealous for the Lord of hoſts,
<note place="margin">Numb. 29.9.</note> haue no courage for the truth;
<note place="margin">Ierem. 9.3.</note> when they that ſhould preſerue equitie and iuſtice, turne iudgement into wormwood,
<note place="margin">Amos 5.2.</note> and leaue off righteouſnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth; when gifts doe blinde the eies of the wiſe,
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.8.</note> and peruert the words of the righteous; when they doe the greateſt wrongs that ſit in higheſt roomes, when iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:2273:84"/>and authoritie ſhall kiſſe each other, and the workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie will not bee controlled, and cannot bee corrected: Is it not then high time for thee, Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 82.</note> to put to thine hand? is it not time for thee, Iudge of all the earth, to ariſe to iudgement?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The noble ſonnes of Zion compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to fine gold,
<note place="margin">In Nobles.</note> how</hi> are they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come dimme?
<note place="margin">Lament. 4.2.7.8.</note> our <hi>Nazarits that were purer then the ſnow, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the milke,</hi> now their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is blacker then a coale, that men <hi>cannot know the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtreets:</hi> the greateſt of many maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> forget the greateſt,
<note place="margin">Amos 6.1.</note> honour and pleaſure ſteale away their heart. They that are <hi>at eaſe in Zion, truſt in the mountaine of Samaria:</hi> They <hi>put farre from</hi> them <hi>the euill day,
<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> and approch to the ſeate of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:
<note place="margin">Verſe 4.</note> They lie vpon their beds of Iuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and eate the lambes of the flock, and the calues out of the ſtall:
<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> They ſing to the ſound of the viole, and
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:2273:85"/>inuent vnto themſelues the instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of muſicke: They drink wine in bowles,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> and anoint themſelues with the chiefe ointments; but no man is ſorrie for the affliction of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph: They ſay vnto God, Depart from vs, we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies:
<note place="margin">Iob 21.14.15.</note> Who is the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that wee ſhould ſerue him, and what profit ſhould wee haue, if wee ſhould pray vnto him?</hi> If the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets in their daies did bewaile theſe things, what ſhould we do? wee that liue in theſe deſperate diſeaſed times, wherein the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge of wickedneſſe hath almoſt couered the higheſt mountaines of godlineſſe, wherein the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of goodnes are ſo wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therbeaten, that impietie and impunitie hath almoſt left no character thereof vndefaced, the ruſt of irreligiouſnes hath eaten into the moſt ſteelie tempers of our age.</p>
                  <p>Yet if theſe ſinnes were few,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:2273:85"/>(though, as we ſee, they be not to be found in few) yet might ſome hope of pardon bee,
<note place="margin">All ſorts of ſinne in this land.</note> vntill they fild the meaſure, and came to the height of ſinne. But now (alaſſe) this meaſure is alreadie full: As ſin abounds in euery ſort of men, ſo is there to bee found amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery ſort of ſin. What towne or village is there but is polluted with ſome of <hi>Dauids</hi> fooles,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> Pſal. 14.1.</note> that ſay within their <hi>heart, There is no God,</hi> and therefore liue as if there were no heauen nor hell,
<note place="margin">Act. 23.8.</note> no Saint nor Diuell, nor God at all?
<note place="margin">Papiſme.</note> How many thouſands of <hi>Manna</hi>-loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Papiſts ſwarm euery where within our coaſts,
<note place="margin">Exod. 16.3.</note> whoſe mouths are watring after the fleſhpots of Egypt againe, and whoſe hearts are thirſting after the Circean dregs of the purple whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon?
<note place="margin">Reuel. 17.</note> Think we that God doth not ſee what is done in many houſes of the land? <hi>The children gather wood,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 7.18.</note> and the fathers kindle
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:2273:86"/>the fire, and the women knead the dough to make cakes to the Queene of Heauen, and to powre out drinke offerings to other gods.</hi> Theſe <hi>thine aduerſaries,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.4.</note> O Lord, rore in the middeſt of thy congregation, and ſet vp their banners for tokens. They goe to and fro,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.6.</note> and barke like dogs, and runne about the citie.</hi> Theſe Cananites are as prickes vnto our ſides,
<note place="margin">Ioſh. 23.13.</note> and as thornes in our eyes: They gnaſh their teeth at the proſperitie of thy Sanctuarie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> and <hi>crie downe with it, down with it euen to the ground.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea,
<note place="margin">Irreligiouſnes.</note> Lord, thy Sanctuary is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie too much polluted, and the dwelling place of thy name too much alas deſpiſed,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.7. Verſe 6.</note> for they breake downe the carued worke thereof with axes and hammers. Euery priuate mans garden is a paradiſe,
<note place="margin">Greenham.</note> and their fields a garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but the Lords garden (whether for want of manuring, or for the ſleeping of the dreſſers) lieth like
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:2273:86"/>the field of the ſluggiſh man:
<note place="margin">Prouerbs.</note> when euerie houſe is curiouſlie fieled, and euerie citie aptly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted, the houſe of the Lord li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth void in many places, ſo that they that paſſe by are conſtrained to ſay, O Lord,
<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> why doeſt thou behold vs thus and ſuffer vs to ſee ſo great vaſtation? If theeues had come by night,
<note place="margin">Sacriledge.</note> would they not haue ſtolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> till they had enough? If the grape gatherers had come,
<note place="margin">Obad. 5.6.</note> would they not haue left ſome grapes? <hi>O, but how are the things of Eſau ſought vp, and his treaſures ſearched?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioel 1.7.</note> Is not the barke pild off from euery pleaſant tree? how is it made bare? is there one branch which the enemie hath not made white?
<note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> That which the <hi>Palmer worme hath left, the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker worme hath eaten; that which the Canker worme hath left, the Caterpiller hath eaten.</hi> Thus haue they ſpoiled the Church from hand to hand: <hi>O Lord, how long
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:2273:87"/>ſhall the aduerſarie reproch thee?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.10. Verſ. 22.</note> ſhall the enemie blaſpheme thy name for euer? Ariſe, O God, maintaine thine owne cauſe,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> remember the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproch which is offered vnto thy name.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>The contempt of the word.</hi> Ierem. 6.10.</note> For why, thy word, O Lord, is vnto them a reproch, they haue no delight in it: <hi>The children of thy people talk of thee by the walles, and in the doores of their houſes, and ſpeake one to another, ſaying, Come and heare what is the word that commeth from the Lord: They come indeed vnto thee as people vſe to come, and they ſit downe before thee,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.30.31.32.</note> and heare thy words, but they will not doe them; for with their mouthes they make ieſts, and their heart goeth after couetouſnes, and loe, thy Prophets are vnto them as a ieſting ſong of one that hath a pleaſant voice, they heare their words but doe them not.</hi> And which is worſe,
<note place="margin">Light account of Gods benefits.</note> 
                     <hi>there is no balme at Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead,</hi> no means of medicine wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the health of the daughter of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:2273:87"/>this people might be recouered: for they will not be wrapped,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.22. Iſai. 1.6.</note> nor bound vp, nor mollified with oile. This people hath an vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and rebellious heart, they are departed and gone.
<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.23.24.25.</note> They ſay not in their heart, <hi>Let vs now feare the Lord our God, that giueth raine both early and late</hi> in due ſeaſon, <hi>and reſerueth vnto vs the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted weekes of the harueſt:</hi> yea our iniquities haue ſometimes tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away many of theſe things, and our ſins haue hindred good things from vs:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Slight regard of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Iſai. 1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>The oxe knoweth his owner, and the aſſe his masters crib, but our Iſrael will not know, this people will not vnderstand: Thou haſt ſtricken them, O Lord, but they haue not ſorrowed: Thou haſt conſumed them,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.3. <hi>Hardnes of hart.</hi>
                        </note> but they haue refuſed to receiue correction, they haue made their faces harder then a ſtone, and haue refuſed to returne: yea they haue made a couenant with death, and with hell are at agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:2273:88"/>ſaying,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 28.15.</note> Though a ſcourge run ouer and paſſe through, it ſhall not come to vs: for we haue made falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood our refuge, and vnder vanitie are we hid. This thou ſeeſt, O Lord,</hi> and canſt thou ſuffer it? <hi>or ſhall not thy ſoule be auenged on ſuch a nation as this?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ierem. 5 9.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>When as for ſwearing &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming,
<note place="margin">Swearing and blaſpheming.</note> from the names of ſins, they are now ſhrouded vnder the habit of ingenuitie and valour,
<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> and he is counted a Precifian that maketh a conſcience of an oath,
<note place="margin">Iam. 2.6.</note> when the very aire is polluted with blaſphemous ſpeeches, and euery little child, as if their tungs were ſet on fire of hell, can rent and teare thy ſacred body, Chriſt, and the whole land groane vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der othes;
<note place="margin">Ierem. 23.10.</note> canſt thou ſee it, Lord, and ſuffer it, that what thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt for ſo capitall a crime, men ſhould count it for a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious vertue?
<note place="margin">Sabbath brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</note> When thy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, Lord, whoſe ſanctification
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:2273:88"/>thou enioyneſt ſo ſtraitly,
<note place="margin">Gen. 2.23. Exod. 20.11. Heb. 4.4.</note> and giueſt vs a memorandum ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly <hi>to make</hi> it our <hi>delight, and to conſecrate it,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.13.</note> as glorious</hi> vnto thee, are not onely now polluted with fearefull prophanation, but alſo called into irreligious que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, when there is almoſt no wickedneſſe which is not eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially committed vpon this day,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bucer. in Pſal.</hi> 92</note> it being peruerted from the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of the Lord to the pleaſures of the fleſh,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Muſcul. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> 4.</note> and from the honour of the great and high God to the rites of <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> and ſo made the Diuels high holiday with many: Wilt not thou for this <hi>kindle a fire in the gates of our Zion?</hi> and ſhall it not <hi>deuoure the palaces of Ieruſalem?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When whoredome and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie are eſteemed as trickes of youth, and vſurie, conſenage,
<note place="margin">Adulterie and whoredome.</note> and oppreſſion as things indifferent; when the adulteries of men are written in their foreheads, and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:2273:89"/>the whoredome of women be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene their breaſts,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 8.12.</note> when they are not aſhamed that doe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit theſe things, neither can bee brought to any ſhame: but though <hi>thou feedeſt them to the full,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.7.8.9.</note> yet they commit adulterie, and aſſemble themſelues by companies in the harlots houſes, and riſe vp in the morning like fed horſes, euery man neighing after his neighbours wife.</hi> When whoredomes <hi>prodromus</hi> or pandar Pride doth ſo taint and infect all degrees,
<note place="margin">Pride.</note> and the vanitie of all other natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s is little enough to make vp the meaſure of an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh follie: When <hi>the daughters of Zion are haughtie,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 3.19.</note> and walke with ſtretched out neckes, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring eyes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 1.27.</note> and men effeminate to faſhion themſelues according to the world onely,
<note place="margin">Rom. 12.1. Rom. 13.4.</note> making it their onely thought to fulfill the luſts of the fleſh: When <hi>the ſtone crieth out of the wall,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Couetouſnes.</hi> Hab. 2.11.</note> and the beame out of the timber anſwereth it</hi> againſt the
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:2273:89"/>common practiſe of thoſe <hi>that ioyne houſe to houſe, and lay field to field,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 5.8.</note> till there be no place for the poore, that they may bee placed by themſelues in the midſt of the earth:</hi> when <hi>euery one hunteth his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a net,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mich. 7.2. Hab. 1.16.</note> and <hi>ſacrifice to their yearne,</hi> and to their net: and as a cage is full of birds,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 5.27.</note> ſo are their houſes full of deceit, by which they are become great and waxen rich: When the fat buls of Baaſhan gore the ſheepe of the flocke,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> Pſal. 22.12.</note> and the rich men ſwallow vp the poore, <hi>that they may make the needie of the land to faile, and the ſellers make the Ephah ſmall,
<note place="margin">Amos 8.4.5.6.</note> and the Shekel great, and falſifie the waights by deceit, that they may buy the poore for ſiluer, and the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die for ſhooes:</hi> Is it not then time for thee, O God, to whom <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance belongeth,</hi> to ſhew thy ſelf?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Ariſe thou</hi> indge of the world, <hi>and reward the proud after their deſeruing,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.16.</note> for the poore committeth
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:2273:90"/>himſelfe vnto thee, who art the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the fatherleſſe and needie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When Court and Countrie ſwarmes with deſperat hackſters braules,
<note place="margin">Crueltie and quarrelling.</note> with whom rapine, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, malice, and murther are but veniall ſinnes, which yet like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> blood from out of the earth doe crie vnto the Lord:
<note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note> When men <hi>riſe vp early to follow drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes,
<note place="margin">Drunkennes.</note> and continue till night, vntil the wine doe inflame them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 5.11.</note> and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it a point of valour to bee mightie to drink wine, &amp; ſtrong to powre in ſtrong drinke.
<note place="margin">Verſ. 22.</note> And Sodoms trinitie of maſter ſinnes, pride,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 16.40. <hi>Idlenes.</hi>
                     </note> fulnes of bread, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of idlenes, abound in vs; there being ſo many millions that liue inordinately amongſt vs:
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.11.</note> and ſo many walking the ſluggards pace, of whom the heauenly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath told vs ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<note place="margin">Philip. 3.18.19.</note> yea and told vs weeping, that <hi>they are enemies to the croſſe of Chriſt, whoſe end is damnation, whoſe god is their
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:2273:90"/>bellie, whoſe glorie is their ſhame, which minde earthly things.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Vnfaithfulnes.</note> When there is no truſt to be repoſed in a friend,
<note place="margin">Mich. 7.5.</note> nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence in a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller, and the doores of a mans mouth had neede bee locked vp from her that lieth in his boſome; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whole land like a bowle is ouerſwaied by the ſtrong bias of iniquitie,
<note place="margin">Nothing but ſin.</note> and bends without oppoſition to black corruption: when there is no care of <hi>truth,
<note place="margin">Hoſea 4.1.2.</note> nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the land, but by lying, and ſwearing, and killing, and ſtealing and whoring men breake out, and blood toucheth blood:</hi> Can there be a God, and he not ſee? can he ſee and not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh theſe ſo vile abominations?</p>
                  <p>No, no,
<note place="margin">It agreeth with the equitie of Gods inſtice to puniſh theſe ſins.</note> thou art a God of pure eyes, and canſt not endure the ſight of euill: Thou art iealous of thy glorie, and will not hold him guiltleſſe that ſhall prophane thy name;
<note place="margin">Hab. 1.13.</note> thou wilt not ſurely <hi>cleere the innocent,</hi> but wilt <hi>viſit the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:2273:91"/>of the fathers vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<note place="margin">Deut. 5.11. Exod. 34.7.</note> and vpon the childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren vnto the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> Art not thou the ſame that whurledſt downe angels fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heauen becauſe of their ſins,
<note place="margin">Ierem. 32.18.</note> and madeſt Sodome and Gomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rha,
<note place="margin">God is no leſſe bent to puniſh ſinne now then heretofore.</note> which ſometimes were as an other Eden, a breeding place for nettles, and a lake of aſhes? yea thou didſt not ſpare Ieruſalem thine owne ſelected city,
<note place="margin">Iude 6. 2. Pet. 2.4. Geneſ. 13.10. Geneſ. 19.24. Ierem. 25.29. Matth. 24.3. Iſai. 59.1. Heb. 1.11.</note> but haſt made it for ſin an heape of ſtones: yea, Lord, thine hand is not ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſtrike, nor thine eares heauie, that they cannot heare: Thou art ſtill the ſame, and thine hatred againſt ſin now as great as euer it hath been.</p>
                  <p>Or haue wee a greater priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to pleade vpon then other people had?
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>We haue no more priuiledge to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure vi fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods iudgements, then other nations had.</hi> Nahum 3.8.</note> Are wee better then <hi>No</hi> which was full of people, that lay in the riuers, and had the waters round about it, whoſe ditch was from the ſea, and her
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:2273:91"/>wall from Egypt to Ethiopia, yet ſhe was carried away and went into captiuitie? Are wee in ſafer ſhelter then the people of other countries, who for their ſins are rooted vp as though they had not been planted, as though their ſtocke had taken no roote in the earth?
<note place="margin">Iſai. 41.24.</note> the Lord hath blown vpon them, and they are withered, and the whirlewind like ſtubble hath taken them away: yea the Lord hath not <hi>ſpared the city wherein</hi> his <hi>own name was called vpon;
<note place="margin">Ierem. 25.29.</note> and ſhal</hi> we <hi>goe free?</hi> O no, it is impoſſible, it cannot bee. The Lord hath ſworne by his holineſſe,
<note place="margin">Amos 4.2.</note> that his eye ſhal not ſpare, neither will he haue pitie, but will powre out his wrath and fulfill his anger in vs,
<note place="margin">Ezech. 7.8.9.</note> and pay vs home according to our waies, and of the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are in the midſt of vs.
<note place="margin">Ierem. 7.16.</note> Bootleſſe, ah I feare, is it to lift vp crie or prayers againſt the ſame: for though <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel</hi> ſtood before him to entreat him,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:2273:92"/>yet how could his affection bee towards this ſo ſinfull people?
<note place="margin">Ierem. 15.1.</note> Though hitherto hee hath for a long time held his peace,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 42.14.</note> yet now hee will deſtroy and deuoure at once.</p>
                  <p>Yea verely,
<note place="margin">What the reaſon is why theſe iudgements haue not alreadie ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on vs.</note> it is the Lords mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie that we are not yet conſumed: for we had long ere this haue bin as Sodome, and our countrie as Gomorrha, had not ſome zealous <hi>Phineahſes</hi> delaied his wrath, and ſome of his choſen <hi>Moſeſes</hi> ſtood in the breach before him to turne away his wrath,
<note place="margin">Lament. 3.22. Zeph. 2.9. Numb. 25.11.</note> leſt hee ſhould deſtroy them. But now, alas, theſe <hi>righteous men decay</hi> apace,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 106.23.</note> 
                     <hi>and no man conſidereth it in his hart; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful men are taken away, &amp; no man vnderſtandeth that they are taken away from the euill to come.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai 57.1.</note> What hope of health now, when there is ſcarſe a godly man left,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.1.</note> and the faithfull are diminiſhed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of men? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now the daies of our viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt needs be neere,
<note place="margin">The neere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Gods iudgements.</note> the daies
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:2273:92"/>of recompence are comming, Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhall know it, our ſelues,
<note place="margin">Hoſea 9.9.</note> our wiues, our children, I feare ſhall ſhortly feele it. Me thinks I heare already the noiſe of the whip,
<note place="margin">Nahum 2.2.</note> and the mouing of the wheeles, the axe is alreadie lifted vp and ready for the ſtroke.</p>
                  <p>O would to God our Elders would ſanctifie a faſt,
<note place="margin">What the way is to preuent Gods iudgements.</note> and our Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord would weepe between the porch and the altar, and cry, <hi>Spare, Lord,
<note place="margin">Ioel 2.15.16.</note> ſpare thy people,</hi> and all the people from the higheſt to the loweſt would turne to the Lord with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<note place="margin">Verſ. 12.</note> weeping and with mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;
<note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>who knoweth whether the Lord wil returne, and</hi> yet ſpare <hi>and leaue a bleſſing behind him?</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe our <hi>God is gratious and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, ſlow to anger, and of great kindnes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, Lord,
<note place="margin">What to do when Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall ſeaſe on vs.</note> if the decree bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie come forth and cannot be reuoked, yet, Lord, correct vs, <hi>but with iudgement, not in thine anger,</hi>
                     <pb n="174" facs="tcp:2273:93"/>leſt we be conſumed and brought to nothing.
<note place="margin">Ierem. 10.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Powre out thy wrath rather vpon the Heathen that know thee not, and vpon the families that call not vpon thy name.</hi> Or if there be no remedie, yet well I know, that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> midſt of theſe his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments God is louing vnto Iſrael,
<note place="margin">Pſalme.</note> to ſuch as are true of heart: He <hi>will deliuer</hi> them <hi>from ſix troubles,
<note place="margin">Iob 5.19.</note> and in the ſeuenth the euill ſhall not touch</hi> them:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.24.</note> they may haue a fall, but they ſhall neuer be caſt off. Al things euen Gods greateſt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly iudgements work for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beſt to Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note> 
                     <hi>for Sions ſake I will not hold my tongue,</hi> but mourne for her deſolations. As for mine own part I will reſt my ſelfe vpon <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> reſolution;
<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.25.</note> 
                     <hi>If I ſhall finde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour in the eyes of the Lord, he will bring me againe, and ſhew me both it, and the Tabernacle thereof: but if hee thus ſay, I haue no delight in thee: Behold here am I, let him doe to me as ſeemeth good in his eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb n="175" facs="tcp:2273:93"/>
                  <p>THE SINNERS Doome: Or, A SVRVEY OF THE wretched eſtate of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked both in this life, and <hi>in the life to come.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <head>TO MY WORTHIE and much reſpected friend, Miſtris <hi>Mary Prime.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
                     <hi>Began with a taſte of happineſſe, and now I end with a taſte of wretchednes. Both of theſe are neceſſarie to be knowne, that wee may loue the one, and
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:2273:94"/>feare the other. I dedicate this my laſt theorem vnto you, not as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to your condition, but as an Amulet for your conſolation: For I beare you record that you haue alreadie taſted</hi> how ſweet the Lord is,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.8.</note> 
                     <hi>you haue had a taſte</hi> of the good word of God,
<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4.5.</note> and of the powers ofthe world to come, <hi>and haue found them ſweeter to your ſoule</hi> then the honey and the honey combe.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 19 10. Luke. 10.6.</note> 
                     <hi>And I am well aſſured that you are a childe of peace, far free from that portion which here my following treatiſe deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth to be the ſinners legacie: for I haue had experience of your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained faith in Chriſt, your loue to his word,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.3.</note> and delight in his Saints. I therefore commend this little Pamphlet to your medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to ſtir you vp more &amp; more
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:2273:94"/>to thankſgiuing vnto God,
<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.13.</note> who hath called you out of darknes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this maruellous light,
<note place="margin">Iohn 15.19.</note> and hath choſen you out of the world that you ſhould not periſh with the world. Doubtleſſe the peace of conſcience,
<note place="margin">Philip. 4.7.</note> that peace which the godly doe enioy, is an inualuable treaſure, it paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: This peace ſhall euer be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Iſrael of God, though there be no peace at al vnto the wicked. As you therefore haue begun in the ſpirit, ſo I ceaſe not to pray for you,
<note place="margin">Coloſ. 1.9.10.5.</note> that you</hi> may be fulfilled with the knowledge <hi>of the</hi> wil <hi>of God</hi> in all wiſedom and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, that you may walk worthy of the Lord, and pleaſe him in all things, being fruitful in al good works, and encreaſing in the knowledge of God, for the hopes ſake
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:2273:95"/>which is laid vp for you in heauen: <hi>whereof you haue heard before by the word of truth, which by me and others hath bin prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto you. And here I leaue with you theſe following medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as a teſtimony of my thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full remembrance of many kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which you haue ſhewed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and not to me alone, but to all thoſe which come in the name of a Prophet amongſt you.
<note place="margin">Matth. 10.41.</note> Reade, meditate, and vſe it to your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and the God of peace ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you both in ſoule and bodie, and keepe you with all yours blameles vntill the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours euer in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, <hi>G. W.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="179" facs="tcp:2273:95"/>
                  <head>THE SINNERS Doome.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ISAI. 57.21.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>There is no peace, ſaith my God, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wicked.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ret not thy ſelf</hi> (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid) becauſe of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlie,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.1.2.</note> neither bee thou enuious for the euill doers: for they ſhall ſoone be cut downe like graſſe, and wither as the greene hearbe.</hi> Me thinkes it ſhould be an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to diſſwade any man from en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying them, who are rather to be pitied becauſe they are ſet <hi>in ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie places,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The ſeeming proſperitie of the wicked.</note> rather to be lamented becauſe their eſtate is ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, fickle, and full of woe. For albeit theſe are they that ſeeme to proſper in the world, and to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:2273:96"/>encreaſe in riches,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.12.5.7.</note> which <hi>are luſty and ſtrong, and not in trouble like other men, their eyes ſtand out for fatnes, and they haue more then heart can wiſh.</hi> Though <hi>they liue and waxe old,
<note place="margin">Iob 21.7.8.9.10</note> and grow in wealth, their ſeed is eſtabliſhed in their ſight with them, and their generation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes. Their houſes are peaceable and without feare, and the rod of God is not vpon them: Their bullock ingendreth and faileth not, their cow calueth and caſteth not her calfe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.11.</note> Though <hi>they thinke their houſes and their habitations ſhall continue for euer, euen from gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to generation, and call their lands by their names.</hi> Though the people fall downe vnto them, and they be deemed the only happie men in the world:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The vnmasking of the wicked.</hi> Pſal. 73.17.18.</note> yet let a man but goe into the Sanctuary of the Lord, &amp; ſeek to vnderſtand their end, and he ſhall finde that their <hi>wealth is not in their own hand,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 21.16.17.18.</note> but they are ſet in ſlippery places, and
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:2273:96"/>their change is fearefull. O how oft ſhall the <hi>candle of the wicked be put out, and their deſtruction come vpon them at vnawares! he ſhall be as ſtubble before the winde, and as chafe that the ſtorme carieth away. O how ſuddenly are they destroyed, periſhed, and horribly conſumed!
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.19.20.</note> as a dreame when one awaketh, ſo ſhall the Lord make their image deſpiſed.</hi> For why?
<note place="margin">Iob 21.30.</note> the wicked is kept but as a ſtalled oxe vnto the day of deſtruction, &amp; he ſhal be brought foorth vnto the day of wrath: In the hand of the Lord <hi>there is a cup, &amp; the wine is red, it is ful mixt,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 75.8.</note> and hee powreth out of the ſame; ſurely the wicked of the earth ſhall wring out and drink the dregs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi> This is Gods iuſt doome vpon them, they ſhal be like the <hi>raging of the ſea, that cannot reſt,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 57.20.21.</note> whoſe</hi> waters <hi>caſt vp dirt and mire. There is no peace, ſaith my God, to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſurely how true this reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:2273:97"/>doome of wicked wretches is,
<note place="margin">The reſtleſſe and wretched eſtate of the wicked euen in this life.</note> who ſeeth not, that hath but an eye to ſee, and an heart to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand? <hi>whoſe mouthes</hi> though they <hi>bee ſet againſt heauen;
<note place="margin">Pſal. 73.9.6.</note> and their tongue walketh through the earth,</hi> though <hi>pride</hi> be <hi>a chaine vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and crueltie couereth them like a garment:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 21.9.</note> Though the <hi>houſes</hi> of their hearts ſeeme <hi>peaceable and without feare:</hi> yet, God he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, their dolefull mindes are toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp and downe with many a blaſt of anguiſh, and blowne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with many a gale of terror, like ſurging waues which rage vpon the ſeas,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pompon. Mel. lib.</hi> 2.</note> and like <hi>Euripus</hi> which euer boyleth and is in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall agitation. <hi>The wicked man is continually as one that trauelleth with child,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 15.20.21.</note> oppreſſed with inward throbs and gripes of heart; <hi>A ſound of feare is euer in his eares, terrors ſhall take him as waters,
<note place="margin">Iob 27.20.21.</note> and tempest ſhall carrie him away by night, the caſt winde ſhall take him
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:2273:97"/>away,
<note place="margin">Prou. 28.1.</note> and hee ſhall flie when none purſueth him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And why?
<note place="margin">The worme of conſcience.</note> there is a worme that neuer dieth, which is alwaies nibling at their hearts, and, like the Poets furies, laſhing their guiltie conſcience with accuſing horror.
<note place="margin">Mark 9.44.</note> In the middeſt of all their hearts delights &amp; pleaſing mirth, there appeares an hand writing before their eies which troubleth their thoughts within them, and maketh the ioynts of their loines looſe,
<note place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> and their knees to ſmite the one againſt the other. Whiles they ſeeme to enioy their chiefeſt iollitie, there hangeth ouer their head a waightie ſword by a ſmall twine of threed; when they full faine would put God out of their mindes,
<note place="margin">Amos 6.3.</note> and put the euil day farre from their thoughts, and would reioice in their youth, and cheere vp their heart in their delights; will they, nill they, an heauie hammer knocketh this <hi>memento</hi>
                     <pb n="184" facs="tcp:2273:98"/>into their hearts,
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 11.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Know that for all theſe things God wil bring thee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement.</hi> Yea, his eye ſhall faile with fearfull looking for the dreadfull iudgement and <hi>violent fire which ſhall deuoure the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſay ſome ſenſeleſſe ſoule and cauteriſed conſcience ſhould be ſo faſt aſleepe as not to feele this ſmart,
<note place="margin">Want of feeling this horror of conſcience in the wicked moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperat.</note> as doubtleſſe many ſinners are, yet ſhall wee thinke their caſe as void of feare? No, no, a deadly lethargie poſſeſſeth ſuch mens ſoules, whoſe pangs may well be thought moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous then, when leaſt they are felt, and whoſe eſtate is moſt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible when they are moſt inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible;
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.2.</note> whoſe <hi>conſciences are ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with an hot iron.</hi> O take heede of ſuch, for well wee know that <hi>ſuch a one is peruerted,
<note place="margin">Tit. 3.11.</note> and ſinneth being damned of his owne ſelfe,</hi> and being ſenſeleſſe of his ſinne, is <hi>giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe,
<note place="margin">Rom. 1.24.</note> and
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:2273:98"/>being paſt feeling,
<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.19.</note> giue themſelues ouer to worke all vncleannes euen with greedineſſe:</hi> being alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die within the iawes of hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they bee awares. And well I wote, that when ſuch ſleepie ſoules ſhall awake, (and wake they ſhal, ſecurely now although they ſleepe) that then their hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror ſhall be the greater farre: like wilde beaſts, which though ſo long as they lie aſleepe, ſeeme tame and gentle, yet being rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, are fierce and wrathfull.</p>
                  <p>In the meane,
<note place="margin">Sinners Gods enemies.</note> albeit in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew they may ſeeme ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet let them know their caſe is fearfull: for if the wrath of an earthlie King bee raging, how dreadful then muſt needs be their eſtate who are profeſſed enemies to the King of Heauen?
<note place="margin">Iſai. 26.11.</note> Surely he <hi>hateth all thoſe that worke iniquity,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 5.6.</note> and both the wicked man and his wickednes are in hatred with him.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.</note>
                     <note place="margin">Prou. 15.9.</note> The way of the wicked is an
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:2273:99"/>abomination to the Lord:
<note place="margin">Iſai. 1. Pſal. 50.</note> Hee cannot abide nor permit the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to praiſe him, to pray vnto him, or to take his couenant in his mouth: no maruell then if at the laſt day hee ſhew ſuch rigor vnto them, who in this life are ſo extreamly hated and deteſted of him.
<note place="margin">Gods threatnings againſt ſinners.</note> What peace then can they haue that haue the Lord of hoſts to be their enemie?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>God ſhall raine ſnares of fire vpon ſinners, brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone with tempestuous windes ſhall be the portion of their cuppe:</hi> the Lord ſhall <hi>breake their teeth in their mouthes,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.6.9.10.</note> and ſhoote foorth his arrowes and destroy them:</hi> Hee ſhall <hi>carrie them away as a whirle winde in his wrath,</hi> and <hi>waſh</hi> his <hi>feete in the blood of the vngodlie:</hi> He will <hi>powre out his wrath vpon them, and fulfill all his anger in them:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezech. 7.8.9.10.</note> Hee will <hi>iudge them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their waies, and lay vpon them all their abominations, neither ſhall his eye ſpare them, neither will
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:2273:99"/>he haue pitie on them, and</hi> they <hi>ſhall know that hee is the Lord that ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them. Curſed</hi> be they <hi>in the towne, and curſed in the field, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the fruite of</hi> their <hi>bodie,
<note place="margin">Deut. 28.16.17.18.</note> and curſed in the fruite of</hi> their <hi>land, the increaſe of</hi> their <hi>kine, and in the flocks of</hi> their <hi>ſheepe: curſed when</hi> they <hi>come in, and curſed when</hi> they <hi>goe out:</hi> curſed in their bodies, and curſed in their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>Now then let them boaſt while they will of their proſperitie,
<note place="margin">The beginning of hell here in this life to the wicked.</note> and let ſuch as are like vnto them flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them in their follie: though they ſeeme with Capernaum to be lifted vp to heauen,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.23.</note> yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold alreadie they are in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of hell: though they haue a name of mightineſſe, yet indeed they are in the loweſt eſtate of abiectnes: Though they may ſeeme the only men that liue, yet they are but dead whiles heere they liue:
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6.</note> Though worldlings do admire them,
<note place="margin">Rom. 6.16.</note> yet are they but the
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:2273:100"/>Lords laughing ſtockes, Sinnes ſlaues, and Satans drudges. Poore woodcocks are they enſnared in Satans ſprings,
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.26. Rom. 9.22.</note> veſſels of wrath ordained for the Diuels blacke kitchin, alreadie treading the waies of darkneſſe,
<note place="margin">Prou. 4.19. Exod. 3.</note> the prince of darkneſſe taske me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the works of wickedneſſe: yea they dwell alreadie in the land of darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 107.10.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſt bound in miſerie and iron:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.8.</note> when Gods children are ſatisfied with the dainties of his houſe,
<note place="margin">Luke 15.16.</note> they feed on husks of ſinne and draffe of beaſtly life: when the ſoules of the Saints are tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Ghoſt,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.15. Reuel. 18.2.</note> their ſoules be neſts of Scorpions &amp; dunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Diuels:
<note place="margin">Reuel. 21.27.</note> when Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren haue their names regiſtred in the booke of life, their names are engroſſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> book of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, being alreadie in the power of the Diuell and his angels,
<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.6.</note> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to ſinne and all temptations,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:2273:100"/>dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, whiles in their bodies they bee aliue, and when they die, hauing this death the earneſt penie of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death.</p>
                  <p>For certainly,
<note place="margin">The dolefull eſtate of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the day of death.</note> 
                     <hi>The reioycing of the wicked is but ſhort, and the ioy of hypocrites is but a moment: though his excellencie mount vp to the heauen, &amp; his head reach vnto the clouds,
<note place="margin">Iob 20.5.6.7.8.9.</note> yet ſhall hee periſh for euer like his dung, and they which haue ſeene him ſhall ſay, Where is he? He ſhall flee away as a dreame, and ſhall paſſe away as a viſion in the night: Goe</hi> he ſhall, there is no remedie,
<note place="margin">Iob 10.22.</note> 
                     <hi>into the land of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſhadow of death, into a land, I ſay, darke as darkneſſe it ſelf, and into the ſhadow of death, where is none order, but the light is there as darkneſſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 9. Eccleſ. 3.19.</note> And albeit this is the condition of the iuſt as well as the vniuſt, and as the one dieth ſo muſt the other die and returne vnto the duſt: yet (good Lord)
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:2273:101"/>how great a difference is there betweene the righteous and the wicked at the day of death? <hi>Mark the vpright man,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note> and behold the iuſt for the end of that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is peace:</hi> when ghaſtly death approcheth with her inexorable deſtinie, <hi>then doe they lift vp their heads,
<note place="margin">Luke 21.28.</note> for that their redemptin<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> draweth nigh</hi> from the labours and toyles of this world.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.1.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed then</hi> are they <hi>that feare the Lord, the Lord wil ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them vpon their bed of ſorrow, and make their bed in their ſicknes.</hi> So that with holie <hi>Hilarion,</hi> they then begin to cheere vp their ſoule:
<note place="margin">Hieron. in vita Hilarion. Exito anima mea, exito &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>Goe out my ſoule, goe out, thou needeſt not feare, thus long thou haſt ſerued Chriſt, why ſhoul deſt thou now bee afraid to goe to him?</hi> But for the wicked and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man, as there is no peace to him during the whole courſe of his life; ſo ſhall hee finde leaſt peace at the houre of death. <hi>O Death how bitter is the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 41.</note>
                        <pb n="191" facs="tcp:2273:101"/>of thee to a man that liueth at rest in his poſſeſſions?</hi> how irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſhall it bee to an vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant ſinner, when hee ſhall ſee Death it ſelfe ſtanding before his face to arreſt him, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vnto him with this incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table doome; <hi>Thou ſoule,
<note place="margin">Luke 12.19.</note> this night I must take away thy ſoule from thee, and then whoſe ſhall theſe</hi> thy pleaſures and thy profits <hi>be?</hi> A wofull anguiſh muſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> needs poſſeſſe his heart, when hee muſt part from all his earthly ioyes, pleaſures &amp; commodities which he hath trauelled for with the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his ſoule, and finde no profit in them, but that hee <hi>hath trauelled for the winde.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.15.</note> But what ſhould I ſpeake of the loſſe of theſe toyes and trifles? they muſt part with life it ſelfe:
<note place="margin">Iob 2.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Skinne for skinne, and all that a man hath will hee giue for his life.</hi> But all the wealth and riches in the world cannot purchaſe one houres leaſe
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:2273:102"/>of longer life, Death will claime his due, an inexorable creditor: which when it cannot chuſe but breede an horror in the heart of him that lieth a dying; ſo will it fill his ſoule with direfull griefe to call to minde the vaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of his forepaſſed life, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall ſigh for griefe of mind, and ſay within themſelues; O ſenſeleſſe we and more then fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick fooles, <hi>We haue wearied our ſelues in the way of wickedneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Syracides,</hi> 5.1.3.7.8.9.</note> and wee haue gone through dangerous waies, but we haue not knowne the way of the Lord. What hath our pride profited vs? or what profit hath the pomp of our riches brought vnto vs? all thoſe things doe paſſe away like a ſhadow,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> and as a poſt that paſſeth by.</hi> At that day will God <hi>be knowne of them to be a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible God,</hi> and dreadfull. <hi>Hee will then write bitter things against them,
<note place="margin">Iob 13.26.</note> and make them poſſeſſe the ſinnes of their youth.</hi> The conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:2273:102"/>will come in then with her bill of accounts, and ſhew many old reckonings and arrerages of ſinnes, and Satan will ſhoote foorth many millions of canons of deſperation againſt the ſicke beſieged ſoule, and lay before his eyes the large bedrole of their ſinnes: which when the guiltie conſcience cannot denie, O how it filleth the heart with horror, and ſouſeth the dreadfull ſoule with feare! How bitter and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable is that parting farewell which they make to their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſoule?
<note place="margin">Aelius Adrianus. Animula, vagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, blandula, quae nunc abibis in loca, pallidula, frigida, nudula, &amp;c.</note> like that of <hi>Adrian</hi> the Romane Emperour, when he was now a dying; <hi>My darling ſoule, poore ſoule, poore fleeting wandring ſoule, my bodies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times beſt beloued gheſt and equall, whither art thou now going, pale, wanne, and naked, into places vgly, diſmall, full of horror and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet happie, yea thrice happie
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:2273:103"/>were it,
<note place="margin">The wicked haue no peace after death.</note> if death were the <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrophe</hi> of the ſinners Tragedie, and the end of their being might come with the end of their earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liuing:
<note place="margin">Their ſoules po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to hell.</note> happy were it for them if like to dogges and toads, and beaſts, they might periſh and bee no more, but loe their chiefeſt woe is yet to come: for when <hi>they lie in the graue like ſheep,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.14. Iob 19.26.</note> death gnaweth vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> whiles wormes deſtroy their carkaſe, hell fire ſeaſeth vpon their ſoules, and vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with torments. What ſhall I heere recount the ſudden dreadfull paſſage of their ſoules from the bodie to their doome, dragd downe by furious fiends of hell, vnto their place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.4. Iude 6.</note> where <hi>they ſhall be in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting chaines vnder darknes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to damnation, and to the finall iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great day.</hi> At which day (good Lord) what horror &amp; amazement will affright them? when the vngodly, whoſe bodies
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:2273:103"/>are rotten in the duſt of the earth,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>The horror of the wicked at the day of reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Matth. 25.</note> ſhall on a ſudden be rouſed from their deadly ſleepe by the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of an Angell; and like guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie malefactors, they ſhall come foorth of the filthie dungeon of rottennes to appeare at the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall for their triall.
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> What a dreadfull day will that bee for thoſe that haue paſſed their time ſecurely here in this world? how will they be amazed at the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dennes of this their rouſing vp from the bed of death? What a ſea of miſeries and terrors ſhall ruſh vpon them, when on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den being raiſed vp,
<note place="margin">Matth. 24.30.31.32.33.34.35.36.37.</note> and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled with the ſame robes of their bodies, ſo long laid vp in the wardrope of the duſt, they ſhall heare about their eares ſo hideous a noyſe of Trumpets, ſound of waters, motion of all the elements; when they ſhall ſee the earth reeling and tottering, the hils and dales skipping, the
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:2273:104"/>Moone darkned,
<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.12.</note> the Starres fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe from heauen, the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament ſhiuered in peeces, and all the world in a flaming fire? If <hi>Adam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 3.8.</note> after his eating of the forbidden fruite, would faine haue hid himſelf from God, wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the garden at the coole of the day; how ſhall the deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate forlorne ſinner then abide the preſence of the Iudge,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.7.</note> not walking in the coole of mercie, but comming in flaming fire, and ſitting in his throne of Maieſtie;
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.31. Reuel. 20.12.</note> when the books ſhall be opened, when not onely they ſhall be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to account for their groſſe and hainous ſinnes,
<note place="margin">Matth. 12.36.</note> but ſhall be compelled to <hi>giue account for euery idle word,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> and their verie <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts ſhall be brought to iudgement?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> Alas, what wil thoſe wiſe people doe then that now liue in delights, and count a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian conuerſation fooliſhneſſe? What ſhift will they make in
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:2273:104"/>thoſe extremities? what will they anſwere for themſelues? doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ſhall not be able to <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him one of a thouſand:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 9.3.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will they then turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? Will they hope that the Bill of their Inditement may be loſt?
<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.23.</note> They haue ſmall hope of that, for he, who is their Iudge, <hi>ſearcheth the heart and reines, yea all things are naked and open to his eyes.</hi> Hope they that their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall countenance them out? <hi>Behold he findeth no ſtedfaſtnes in the Angels;
<note place="margin">Iob 4.18.19.</note> how much leſſe then in them that dwell in houſes of clay, and whoſe foundation is in the duſt?</hi> Doe they perſwade themſelues that they can bribe the Iudge? <hi>Loe,
<note place="margin">Prou. 11.4. Matth. 16.16.</note> riches auaile not in the day of wrath; and what ſhall a man giue for a recompence of his ſoule?</hi> Doe they hope vpon a Pſalme of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or a pardon? There was a time indeed when that was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto them, if with repentant
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:2273:105"/>mindes they would haue accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the ſame: but now <hi>there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſin,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.26.27.</note> but a fearfull looking for of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which ſhall deuoure the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.</hi> Good Lord, then what will the wretched ſinner doe at that moſt dolefull day? what ſhift will he make? He ſhall euen drie vp for very feare:
<note place="margin">Matth. 24.</note> 
                     <hi>Hee ſhall ſeeke death, and death ſhall flie from him:
<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.15.16.</note> He ſhall crie to the hils to fall vpon him, and to the mountaines to couer him.</hi> But all in vaine, for there ſhall hee ſtand a deſperate, forlorne, caitiſe wretch, vntill he receiue that dreadfull and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocable ſentence,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.41.</note> 
                     <hi>Goe thou cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> wretch <hi>into euerlasting fire, prepared for the Diuell and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which finall ſentence once pronounced,
<note place="margin">The endleſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked after the day of iudgement.</note> me thinks my heart doth quake to thinke vpon the horror preſentlie ruſhing vpon theſe dammed wretches: what
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:2273:105"/>howling, crying, wailing, and yelling by them will bee made,
<note place="margin">Reuel. 16.9.11.</note> when the infernall officers and fiends of hell with bitter skofes and taunts will hale and dragge them vnto torments?
<note place="margin">Reuel. 16.9.11.</note> then ſhall they curſe the day of their nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie,
<note place="margin">Iob 3.9.10.</note> and wiſh that they neuer had been borne, and that they had periſhed as an vntimelie birth: They ſhall bee readie to rend and teare their ſoules, for that they ſo neglected the time of grace offered vnto them, <hi>There ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth</hi> with them,
<note place="margin">Luke 13.28.</note> when they ſhall ſee <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac and Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> and all the Saints <hi>in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and themſelues thrust out of doores:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 112.10.</note> The vngodly ſhall ſee the happineſſe which they haue loſt, and it ſhall grieue him, <hi>Hee ſhall gnaſh with his teeth and conſume away, and his hope ſhall periſh.</hi> For though like <hi>Diues</hi> they would giue a thouſand thouſand worlds
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:2273:106"/>for <hi>a droppe of cold water to coole</hi> their <hi>tongue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 16.25.</note> they may not haue it. No, no, but whurled ſhall they be to hell,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 66.24.</note> to bee companions with Diuels and damned ſpirits, <hi>in the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone,
<note place="margin">Mark. 9.44.</note> where the worme dieth not, and the fire neuer goeth out.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who is able to dwell in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring fire?
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The paines of Hell.</hi> Iſai. 33.14.</note> or who ſhall be able to dwell in theſe euerlasting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 8.12. 1. Pet. 3.19.</note> The place it ſelfe ſo loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome into which they are caſt, a dungeo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> far more dark the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pitch, worſe then the Egyptian dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which might be felt;
<note place="margin">Exod. 10.21.</note> 
                     <hi>A lake that burneth with fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,
<note place="margin">Matth. 11. Matth. 8.13.</note> where there is weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> In that lake, it is wonderfull to thinke how wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked damned ſoules ſhall be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented day and night:
<note place="margin">Reuel. 10.14.</note> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodie, but ſoule and all with bitter helliſh torments; to which all plagues and torments mans
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:2273:106"/>heart can deuiſe, are but like flea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitings and not to be named: for as the ioyes of heauen are ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> 
                     <hi>as neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, or heart of man can poſſiblie conceiue:</hi> ſo the pains of hell are ſuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue of men or Angels cannot vtter, nor any thought imagine. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie be they that heare, and feare, but neuer feele theſe fearefull paines:
<note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> 
                     <hi>for tribulation and anguiſh ſhall be vpon their</hi> euer burning neuer dying ſoules; the ſhame that ſhall couer their faces is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall,
<note place="margin">Iude 7.</note> the fire that ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them is eternall, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that ſhall aſtoniſh them are euerlaſting,
<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.9.</note> the worme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vpon their conſcience neuer dieth,
<note place="margin">Matth. 25.46.</note> and the fire which ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them neuer goeth out; the paines which they ſhall feele ſhal neuer, neuer haue an end.</p>
                  <p>How can I then but pitie thoſe many thouſand ſillie ſoules,
<note place="margin">The application.</note> who
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:2273:107"/>proue themſelues ſuch fooles, as to buy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon,
<note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> at ſo high a price, as will coſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a dreadfull ſetting on for euer? How can I but admire their ſenſeleſſe madneſſe,
<note place="margin">Prou. 14.9.</note> who though they heare and know this doome of ſinners,
<note place="margin">Iob 15.16.</note> yet <hi>make a iest of ſinne, and drinke vp iniquitie like water?</hi> Why ſhould men be like <hi>Thomas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 20.25.</note> that will not beleeue except they ſee?
<note place="margin">Exod. 10.7.</note> and ſo neere of <hi>Pharaos</hi> mind, that will be deſtroied before they leaue their ſins? As for me, ſeeing this is the ſinners portion, I will endeuor as neere as I can to keep my ſelf from ſinne: Surely I ſhall neuer be able to endure the pains of hell, and therefore as neere as God will giue mee grace, I will keepe me farre from them. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no peace to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked, I will not leaue my peace of conſcience for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2273:107"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
